<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="gettingstarted">
    <title>Getting started with Seam, using seam-gen</title>

    <para>The Seam distribution includes a command line utility that makes it really easy to set up an Eclipse project,
        generate some simple Seam skeleton code, and reverse engineer an application from a preexisting database.</para>

    <para>This is the easy way to get your feet wet with Seam, and gives you some ammunition for next time you find
        yourself trapped in an elevator with one of those tedious Ruby guys ranting about how great and wonderful his
        new toy is for building totally trivial applications that put things in databases.</para>

    <para>In this release, seam-gen works best for people with JBoss AS. You can use the generated project with other
        J2EE or Java EE 5 application servers by making a few manual changes to the project configuration.</para>

    <para>You <emphasis>can</emphasis> use seam-gen without Eclipse, but in this tutorial, we want to show you how to
        use it in conjunction with Eclipse for debugging and integration testing. If you don't want to install Eclipse,
        you can still follow along with this tutorial—all steps can be performed from the command line.</para>

    <para>seam-gen is basically just an intricate Ant script wrapped around Hibernate Tools, together with some templates.
        That makes it easy to customize if you need to.</para>

    <section>
        <title>Before you start</title>

        <para>Make sure you have JDK 5 or JDK 6 (see <xref
            linkend="jdk_dependencies"/> for details), JBoss AS 4.2 or 5.0 and Ant 1.7.0, along with recent versions of
            Eclipse, the JBoss IDE plugin for Eclipse and the TestNG plugin for Eclipse correctly installed before
            starting. Add your JBoss installation to the JBoss Server View in Eclipse. Start JBoss in debug mode.
            Finally, start a command prompt in the directory where you unzipped the Seam distribution.</para>

        <para>JBoss has sophisticated support for hot re-deployment of WARs and EARs. Unfortunately, due to bugs in the
            JVM, repeated redeployment of an EAR—which is common during development—eventually causes the JVM to run out
            of perm gen space. For this reason, we recommend running JBoss in a JVM with a large perm gen space at
            development time. If you're running JBoss from JBoss IDE, you can configure this in the server launch
            configuration, under "VM arguments". We suggest the following values:</para>

        <programlisting>-Xms512m -Xmx1024m -XX:PermSize=256m -XX:MaxPermSize=512m</programlisting>

        <para>If you don't have so much memory available, the following is our minimum recommendation:</para>

        <programlisting>-Xms256m -Xmx512m -XX:PermSize=128m -XX:MaxPermSize=256m</programlisting>

        <para>If you're running JBoss from the command line, you can configure the JVM options in
            <literal>bin/run.conf</literal>.</para>

        <para>If you don't want to bother with this stuff now, you don't have to—come back to it later, when you get
            your first <literal>OutOfMemoryException</literal>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Setting up a new project</title>

        <para>The first thing we need to do is configure seam-gen for your environment: JBoss AS installation directory,
            project workspace, and database connection. It's easy, just type:</para>

        <programlisting>cd jboss-seam-2.2.x
seam setup</programlisting>

        <para>And you will be prompted for the needed information:</para>

        <programlisting>~/workspace/jboss-seam$ ./seam setup
Buildfile: build.xml

init:

setup:
     [echo] Welcome to seam-gen :-)
    [input] Enter your project workspace (the directory that contains your Seam projects) [C:/Projects] [C:/Projects]
/Users/pmuir/workspace
    [input] Enter your JBoss home directory [C:/Program Files/jboss-4.2.3.GA] [C:/Program Files/jboss-4.2.3.GA]
/Applications/jboss-4.2.3.GA
    [input] Enter the project name [myproject] [myproject]
helloworld
     [echo] Accepted project name as: helloworld
    [input] Select a RichFaces skin (not applicable if using ICEFaces) [blueSky] ([blueSky], classic, ruby, wine, deepMarine, emeraldTown, sakura, DEFAULT)

    [input] Is this project deployed as an EAR (with EJB components) or a WAR (with no EJB support) [ear]  ([ear], war, )

    [input] Enter the Java package name for your session beans [com.mydomain.helloworld] [com.mydomain.helloworld]
org.jboss.helloworld
    [input] Enter the Java package name for your entity beans [org.jboss.helloworld] [org.jboss.helloworld]

    [input] Enter the Java package name for your test cases [org.jboss.helloworld.test] [org.jboss.helloworld.test]

    [input] What kind of database are you using? [hsql]  ([hsql], mysql, oracle, postgres, mssql, db2, sybase, enterprisedb, h2)
mysql
    [input] Enter the Hibernate dialect for your database [org.hibernate.dialect.MySQLDialect] [org.hibernate.dialect.MySQLDialect]

    [input] Enter the filesystem path to the JDBC driver jar [lib/hsqldb.jar] [lib/hsqldb.jar]
/Users/pmuir/java/mysql.jar
    [input] Enter JDBC driver class for your database [com.mysql.jdbc.Driver] [com.mysql.jdbc.Driver]

    [input] Enter the JDBC URL for your database [jdbc:mysql:///test] [jdbc:mysql:///test]
jdbc:mysql:///helloworld
    [input] Enter database username [sa] [sa]
pmuir
    [input] Enter database password [] []

    [input] skipping input as property hibernate.default_schema.new has already been set.
    [input] Enter the database catalog name (it is OK to leave this blank) [] []

    [input] Are you working with tables that already exist in the database? [n]  (y, [n], )
y
    [input] Do you want to drop and recreate the database tables and data in import.sql each time you deploy? [n]  (y, [n], )
n
    [input] Enter your ICEfaces home directory (leave blank to omit ICEfaces) [] []

[propertyfile] Creating new property file: /Users/pmuir/workspace/jboss-seam/seam-gen/build.properties
     [echo] Installing JDBC driver jar to JBoss server
     [echo] Type 'seam create-project' to create the new project

BUILD SUCCESSFUL
Total time: 1 minute 32 seconds
~/workspace/jboss-seam $ </programlisting>

        <para>The tool provides sensible defaults, which you can accept by just pressing enter at the prompt.</para>

        <para>The most important choice you need to make is between EAR deployment and WAR deployment of your project.
            EAR projects support EJB 3.0 and require Java EE 5. WAR projects do not support EJB 3.0, but may be deployed
            to a J2EE environment. The packaging of a WAR is also simpler to understand. If you installed an EJB3-ready
            application server like JBoss, choose <literal>ear</literal>. Otherwise, choose <literal>war</literal>.
            We'll assume that you've chosen an EAR deployment for the rest of the tutorial, but you can follow exactly
            the same steps for a WAR deployment.</para>

        <para>If you are working with an existing data model, make sure you tell seam-gen that the tables already exist
            in the database.</para>

        <para>The settings are stored in <literal>seam-gen/build.properties</literal>, but you can also modify them
            simply by running <literal>seam setup</literal> a second time.</para>

        <para>Now we can create a new project in our Eclipse workspace directory, by typing:</para>

        <programlisting>seam new-project</programlisting>

        <programlisting>C:\Projects\jboss-seam&gt;seam new-project
Buildfile: build.xml

...

new-project:
     [echo] A new Seam project named 'helloworld' was created in the C:\Projects directory
     [echo] Type 'seam explode' and go to http://localhost:8080/helloworld
     [echo] Eclipse Users: Add the project into Eclipse using File &gt; New &gt; Project and select General &gt; Project (not Java Project)
     [echo] NetBeans Users: Open the project in NetBeans

BUILD SUCCESSFUL
Total time: 7 seconds
C:\Projects\jboss-seam&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>This copies the Seam jars, dependent jars and the JDBC driver jar to a new Eclipse project, and generates
            all needed resources and configuration files, a facelets template file and stylesheet, along with Eclipse
            metadata and an Ant build script. The Eclipse project will be automatically deployed to an exploded
            directory structure in JBoss AS as soon as you add the project using <literal>New -&gt; Project...
                -&gt; General -&gt; Project -&gt; Next</literal>, typing the <literal>Project name</literal>
                (<literal>helloworld</literal> in this case), and then clicking <literal>Finish</literal>. Do not select
                <literal>Java Project</literal> from the New Project wizard.</para>

        <para>If your default JDK in Eclipse is not a Java SE 5 or Java SE 6 JDK, you will need to select a Java SE 5
            compliant JDK using <literal>Project -&gt; Properties -&gt; Java Compiler</literal>.</para>

        <para>Alternatively, you can deploy the project from outside Eclipse by typing <literal>seam explode</literal>.</para>

        <para>Go to <literal>http://localhost:8080/helloworld</literal> to see a welcome page. This is a facelets page,
                <literal>view/home.xhtml</literal>, using the template <literal>view/layout/template.xhtml</literal>.
            You can edit this page, or the template, in Eclipse, and see the results <emphasis>immediately</emphasis>,
            by clicking refresh in your browser.</para>

        <para>Don't get scared by the XML configuration documents that were generated into the project directory. They
            are mostly standard Java EE stuff, the stuff you need to create once and then never look at again, and they
            are 90% the same between all Seam projects. (They are so easy to write that even seam-gen can do it.)</para>

        <para>The generated project includes three database and persistence configurations. The
            <literal>persistence-test.xml</literal> and
            <literal>import-test.sql</literal> files are used when running the TestNG unit tests against HSQLDB. The
            database schema and the test data in <literal>import-test.sql</literal> is always exported to the database
            before running tests. The <literal>myproject-dev-ds.xml</literal>, <literal>persistence-dev.xml</literal>and
                <literal>import-dev.sql</literal> files are for use when deploying the application to your development
            database. The schema might be exported automatically at deployment, depending upon whether you told seam-gen
            that you are working with an existing database. The <literal>myproject-prod-ds.xml</literal>,
                <literal>persistence-prod.xml</literal>and <literal>import-prod.sql</literal> files are for use when
            deploying the application to your production database. The schema is not exported automatically at
            deployment.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Creating a new action</title>

        <para>If you're used to traditional action-style web frameworks, you're probably wondering how you can create a
            simple web page with a stateless action method in Java. If you type:</para>

        <programlisting>seam new-action</programlisting>

        <para>Seam will prompt for some information, and generate a new facelets page and Seam component for your
            project.</para>

        <programlisting>C:\Projects\jboss-seam&gt;seam new-action
Buildfile: build.xml

validate-workspace:

validate-project:

action-input:
    [input] Enter the Seam component name
ping
    [input] Enter the local interface name [Ping]

    [input] Enter the bean class name [PingBean]

    [input] Enter the action method name [ping]

    [input] Enter the page name [ping]


setup-filters:

new-action:
     [echo] Creating a new stateless session bean component with an action method
     [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\Projects\helloworld\src\hot\org\jboss\helloworld
     [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\Projects\helloworld\src\hot\org\jboss\helloworld
     [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\Projects\helloworld\src\hot\org\jboss\helloworld\test
     [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\Projects\helloworld\src\hot\org\jboss\helloworld\test
     [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\Projects\helloworld\view
     [echo] Type 'seam restart' and go to http://localhost:8080/helloworld/ping.seam

BUILD SUCCESSFUL
Total time: 13 seconds
C:\Projects\jboss-seam&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>Because we've added a new Seam component, we need to restart the exploded directory deployment. You can do
            this by typing <literal>seam restart</literal>, or by running the <literal>restart</literal> target in the
            generated project <literal>build.xml</literal> file from inside Eclipse. Another way to force a restart is
            to edit the file <literal>resources/META-INF/application.xml</literal> in Eclipse. <emphasis>Note that you
                do not need to restart JBoss each time you change the application.</emphasis></para>

        <para>Now go to <literal>http://localhost:8080/helloworld/ping.seam</literal> and click the button. You can see
            the code behind this action by looking in the project <literal>src</literal> directory. Put a breakpoint in
            the <literal>ping()</literal> method, and click the button again.</para>

        <para>Finally, locate the <literal>PingTest.xml</literal> file in the test package and run the integration tests
            using the TestNG plugin for Eclipse. Alternatively, run the tests using <literal>seam test</literal> or the
                <literal>test</literal> target of the generated build.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Creating a form with an action</title>

        <para>The next step is to create a form. Type:</para>

        <programlisting>seam new-form</programlisting>

        <programlisting>C:\Projects\jboss-seam&gt;seam new-form
Buildfile: C:\Projects\jboss-seam\seam-gen\build.xml

validate-workspace:

validate-project:

action-input:
    [input] Enter the Seam component name
hello
    [input] Enter the local interface name [Hello]

    [input] Enter the bean class name [HelloBean]

    [input] Enter the action method name [hello]

    [input] Enter the page name [hello]


setup-filters:

new-form:
     [echo] Creating a new stateful session bean component with an action method
     [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\Projects\hello\src\hot\com\hello
     [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\Projects\hello\src\hot\com\hello
     [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\Projects\hello\src\hot\com\hello\test
     [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\Projects\hello\view
     [copy] Copying 1 file to C:\Projects\hello\src\hot\com\hello\test
     [echo] Type 'seam restart' and go to http://localhost:8080/hello/hello.seam

BUILD SUCCESSFUL
Total time: 5 seconds
C:\Projects\jboss-seam&gt;</programlisting>

        <para>Restart the application again, and go to <literal>http://localhost:8080/helloworld/hello.seam</literal>.
            Then take a look at the generated code. Run the test. Try adding some new fields to the form and Seam
            component (remember to restart the deployment each time you change the Java code).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Generating an application from an existing database</title>

        <para>Manually create some tables in your database. (If you need to switch to a different database, just run
                <literal>seam setup</literal> again.) Now type:</para>

        <programlisting>seam generate-entities</programlisting>

        <para>Restart the deployment, and go to <literal>http://localhost:8080/helloworld</literal>. You can browse the
            database, edit existing objects, and create new objects. If you look at the generated code, you'll probably
            be amazed how simple it is! Seam was designed so that data access code is easy to write by hand, even for
            people who don't want to cheat by using seam-gen.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Generating an application from existing JPA/EJB3 entities</title>

        <para>Place your existing, valid entity classes inside the <literal>src/main</literal>. Now type</para>

        <programlisting>seam generate-ui</programlisting>

        <para>Restart the deployment, and go to <literal>http://localhost:8080/helloworld</literal>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Deploying the application as an EAR</title>

        <para>Finally, we want to be able to deploy the application using standard Java EE 5 packaging. First, we need
            to remove the exploded directory by running <literal>seam unexplode</literal>. To deploy the EAR, we can
            type <literal>seam deploy</literal> at the command prompt, or run the <literal>deploy</literal> target of
            the generated project build script. You can undeploy using <literal>seam undeploy</literal> or the
                <literal>undeploy</literal> target.</para>

        <para>By default, the application will be deployed with the <emphasis>dev profile</emphasis>. The EAR will
            include the <literal>persistence-dev.xml</literal> and <literal>import-dev.sql</literal> files, and the
                <literal>myproject-dev-ds.xml</literal> file will be deployed. You can change the profile, and use the
                <emphasis>prod profile</emphasis>, by typing</para>

        <programlisting>seam -Dprofile=prod deploy</programlisting>

        <para>You can even define new deployment profiles for your application. Just add appropriately named files to
            your project—for example, <literal>persistence-staging.xml</literal>, <literal>import-staging.sql</literal>
            and <literal>myproject-staging-ds.xml</literal>—and select the name of the profile using
                <literal>-Dprofile=staging</literal>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gettingstarted-hotdeployment">
        <title>Seam and incremental hot deployment</title>

        <para>When you deploy your Seam application as an exploded directory, you'll get some support for incremental
            hot deployment at development time. You need to enable debug mode in both Seam and Facelets, by adding this
            line to <literal>components.xml</literal>:</para>

        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<core:init debug="true">]]></programlisting>

        <para>Now, the following files may be redeployed without requiring a full restart of the web application:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>any facelets page</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>any <literal>pages.xml</literal> file</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>But if we want to change any Java code, we still need to do a full restart of the application. (In JBoss
            this may be accomplished by touching the top level deployment descriptor: <literal>application.xml</literal>
            for an EAR deployment, or <literal>web.xml</literal> for a WAR deployment.)</para>

        <para>But if you really want a fast edit/compile/test cycle, Seam supports incremental redeployment of JavaBean
            components. To make use of this functionality, you must deploy the JavaBean components into the
                <literal>WEB-INF/dev</literal> directory, so that they will be loaded by a special Seam classloader,
            instead of by the WAR or EAR classloader.</para>

        <para>You need to be aware of the following limitations:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>the components must be JavaBean components, they cannot be EJB3 beans (we are working on fixing
                    this limitation)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>entities can never be hot-deployed</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>components deployed via <literal>components.xml</literal> may not be hot-deployed</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>the hot-deployable components will not be visible to any classes deployed outside of
                        <literal>WEB-INF/dev</literal></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para>Seam debug mode must be enabled and <literal>jboss-seam-debug.jar</literal>
                   must be in <literal>WEB-INF/lib</literal></para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
               <para>You must have the Seam filter installed in web.xml</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
               <para>You may see errors if the system is placed under any load and debug is enabled.</para>
            </listitem>
            
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>If you create a WAR project using seam-gen, incremental hot deployment is available out of the box for
            classes in the <literal>src/hot</literal> source directory. However, seam-gen does not support
            incremental hot deployment for EAR projects.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Using Seam with JBoss 4.0</title>

        <para> Seam 2 was developed for JavaServer Faces 1.2. When using JBoss AS, we recommend using JBoss 4.2 or
            JBoss 5.0, both of which bundle the JSF 1.2 reference implementation. However, it is still possible to use
            Seam 2 on the JBoss 4.0 platform. There are two basic steps required to do this: install an EJB3-enabled
            version of JBoss 4.0 and replace MyFaces with the JSF 1.2 reference implementation.  Once you complete these
            steps, Seam 2 applications can be deployed to JBoss 4.0.</para>

        <section>
            <title>Install JBoss 4.0</title>
            <para>JBoss 4.0 does not ship a default configuration compatible with Seam. To run Seam, you must install
                JBoss 4.0.5 using the JEMS 1.2 installer with the ejb3 profile selected. Seam will not run with an
                installation that doesn't include EJB3 support. The JEMS installer can be downloaded from <ulink
                    url="http://www.jboss.org/jbossas/downloads"
                >http://www.jboss.org/jbossas/downloads</ulink>. </para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Install the JSF 1.2 RI</title>

            <para> The web configuration for JBoss 4.0 can be found in the
                    <literal>server/default/deploy/jbossweb-tomcat55.sar</literal>. You'll need to delete
                    <literal>myfaces-api.jar</literal> any <literal>myfaces-impl.jar</literal> from the
                    <literal>jsf-libs </literal>directory. Then, you'll need to copy <literal>jsf-api.jar</literal>,
                    <literal>jsf-impl.jar</literal>, <literal>el-api.jar</literal>, and <literal>el-ri.jar</literal>
                to that directory. The JSF JARs can be found in the Seam <literal>lib</literal> directory. The el JARs
                can be obtained from the Seam 1.2 release. </para>

            <para>You'll also need to edit the <literal>conf/web.xml</literal>, replacing
                <literal>myfaces-impl.jar</literal> with <literal>jsf-impl.jar</literal>. </para>
        </section>



    </section>

</chapter>
