<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="guice">

   <title>Guice integration</title>

   <para>
      Google Guice is a library that provides lightweight dependency injection through type-safe
      resolution. The Guice integration (part of the Seam IoC module) allows use of Guice injection
      for all Seam components annotated with the <literal>@Guice</literal> annotation. In addition
      to the regular bijection that Seam performs (which becomes optional), Seam also delegates
      to known Guice injectors to satisfy the dependencies of the component. Guice may be useful to
      tie non-Seam parts of large or legacy applications together with Seam. 
   </para> 

   <note>
      The Guice integration is bundled in the jboss-seam-ioc library. This dependency is required
      for all integration techniques covered in this chapter. You will also need the Guice JAR file
      on the classpath.
   </note>

   <section>
      <title>Creating a hybrid Seam-Guice component</title>

      <para>
         The goal is to create a hybrid Seam-Guice component. The rule for how to do this is very
         simple. If you want to use Guice injection in your Seam component, annotate it with the
         <literal>@Guice</literal> annotation (after importing the type
         <literal>org.jboss.seam.ioc.guice.Guice</literal>).
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@Name("myGuicyComponent")
@Guice public class MyGuicyComponent
{
   @Inject MyObject myObject;
   @Inject @Special MyObject mySpecialObject;
   ...
}</programlisting>

      <para>
          This Guice injection will happen on every method call, just like with bijection. Guice
          injects based on type and binding. To satisfy the dependencies in the previous example,
          you might have bound the following implementations in a Guice module, where
          <literal>@Special</literal> is an annotation you define in your application.
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">public class MyGuicyModule implements Module
{
   public void configure(Binder binder)
   {
      binder.bind(MyObject.class)
         .toInstance(new MyObject("regular"));

      binder.bind(MyObject.class).annotatedWith(Special.class)
         .toInstance(new MyObject("special"));
   }
}</programlisting>
      
      <para>
          Great, but which Guice injector will be used to inject the dependencies?  Well, you need
          to perform some setup first.
      </para>

   </section>

   <section>

      <title>Configuring an injector</title>

      <para>
         You tell Seam which Guice injector to use by hooking it into the injection property
         of the Guice initialization component in the Seam component descriptor (components.xml):
      </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<components xmlns="http://jboss.com/products/seam/components"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xmlns:guice="http://jboss.com/products/seam/guice"
   xsi:schemaLocation="
      http://jboss.com/products/seam/guice
      http://jboss.com/products/seam/guice-2.2.xsd
      http://jboss.com/products/seam/components
      http://jboss.com/products/seam/components-2.2.xsd">

   <guice:init injector="#{myGuiceInjector}"/>

</components>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         <literal>myGuiceInjector</literal> must resolve to a Seam component that implements the
         Guice <literal>Injector</literal> interface.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Having to create an injector is boiler-plate code, though. What you really want to be able
         to do is simply hook up Seam to your Guice modules. Fortunately, there is a built-in Seam
         component that implements the <literal>Injector</literal> interface to do exactly that. You
         can configure it in the Seam component descriptor with this additional stanza.
      </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<guice:injector name="myGuiceInjector">
   <guice:modules>  
      <value>com.example.guice.GuiceModule1</value>  
      <value>com.example.guice.GuiceModule2</value>  
   </guice:modules>  
</guice:injector>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         Of course you can also use an injector that is already used in other, possibly non-Seam
         part of you application. That's one of the main motivations for creating this integration.
         Since the injector is defined with EL expression, you can obtain it in whatever way you
         like. For instance, you may use the Seam factory component pattern to provide injector.
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@Name("myGuiceInjectorFactory")
public InjectorFactory
{
   @Factory(name = "myGuiceInjector", scope = APPLICATION, create = true)
   public Injector getInjector()
   {
      // Your code that returns injector    
   }
}</programlisting>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Using multiple injectors</title>

      <para>
         By default, an injector configured in the Seam component descriptor is used. If you really
         need to use multiple injectors (AFAIK, you should use multiple modules instead), you can
         specify different injector for every Seam component in the <literal>@Guice</literal>
         annotation.
      </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@Name("myGuicyComponent")
@Guice("myGuiceInjector")
public class MyGuicyComponent
{
   @Inject MyObject myObject;
   ...
}</programlisting>
      
   </section>

   <para>
      That's all there is to it! Check out the guice example in the Seam distribution to see the
      Seam Guice integration in action!
   </para>

</chapter>
