<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="gwt">
  <title>Seam and the Google Web Toolkit</title>

  <para>
    For those that prefer to use the Google Web Toolkit (GWT) to develop dynamic AJAX applications, Seam provides
    an integration layer that allows GWT widgets to interact directly with Seam components.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    To use GWT, we assume that you are already familiar with the GWT tools - more information can be found at
    <ulink url="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/">http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/</ulink>.  This chapter 
    does not attempt to explain how GWT works or how to use it.
  </para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>
    
    <para>
      There is no special configuration required to use GWT in a Seam application, however the Seam resource servlet 
      must be installed.  See <xref linkend="configuration"/> for details.
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Preparing your component</title>
    
    <para>
      The first step in preparing a Seam component to be called via GWT, is to create both synchronous and
      asynchronous service interfaces for the methods you wish to call.  Both of these interfaces should extend the
      GWT interface <literal>com.google.gwt.user.client.rpc.RemoteService</literal>:
    </para> 
  
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public interface MyService extends RemoteService {
    public String askIt(String question);      
 }]]></programlisting>
  
    <para>
      The asynchronous interface should be identical, except that it also contains an additional 
      <literal>AsyncCallback</literal> parameter for each of the methods it declares:    
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public interface MyServiceAsync extends RemoteService {
   public void askIt(String question, AsyncCallback callback);
}]]></programlisting>

    <para>
      The asynchronous interface, in this example <literal>MyServiceAsync</literal>, will be implemented by GWT and
      should never be implemented directly.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The next step, is to create a Seam component that implements the synchronous interface:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Name("org.jboss.seam.example.remoting.gwt.client.MyService")
public class ServiceImpl implements MyService {

   @WebRemote
   public String askIt(String question) {
   
      if (!validate(question)) {
         throw new IllegalStateException("Hey, this shouldn't happen, I checked on the client, " +
         "but its always good to double check.");
      }
      return "42. Its the real question that you seek now.";
   }
   
   public boolean validate(String q) {
      ValidationUtility util = new ValidationUtility();
      return util.isValid(q);
   }
}]]></programlisting>

    <para>     
      The name of the seam component <emphasis>must</emphasis> match the fully
      qualified name of the GWT client interface (as shown), or the seam
      resource servlet will not be able to find it when a client makes a GWT
      call. The methods that are to be made accessible via GWT also need to be
      annotated with the <literal>@WebRemote</literal> annotation.      
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Hooking up a GWT widget to the Seam component</title>
    
    <para>
      The next step, is to write a method that returns the asynchronous interface to the component.  This method
      can be located inside the widget class, and will be used by the widget to obtain a reference to the
      asynchronous client stub:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[private MyServiceAsync getService() {       
   String endpointURL = GWT.getModuleBaseURL() + "seam/resource/gwt";      
      
   MyServiceAsync svc = (MyServiceAsync) GWT.create(MyService.class);
   ((ServiceDefTarget) svc).setServiceEntryPoint(endpointURL);
   return svc;     
}]]></programlisting>
   
    <para>
       The final step is to write the widget code that invokes the method on the client stub.  The following example
       creates a simple user interface with a label, text input and a button:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
public class AskQuestionWidget extends Composite {
   private AbsolutePanel panel = new AbsolutePanel();
   
   public AskQuestionWidget() {      
      Label lbl = new Label("OK, what do you want to know?");
      panel.add(lbl);
      final TextBox box = new TextBox();
      box.setText("What is the meaning of life?");
      panel.add(box);
      Button ok = new Button("Ask");
      ok.addClickListener(new ClickListener() {
         public void onClick(Widget w) {
            ValidationUtility valid = new ValidationUtility();
            if (!valid.isValid(box.getText())) {
               Window.alert("A question has to end with a '?'");
            } else {
               askServer(box.getText());
            } 
         }
      });
      panel.add(ok);
      
      initWidget(panel);
   }

   private void askServer(String text) {
      getService().askIt(text, new AsyncCallback() {
         public void onFailure(Throwable t) {
            Window.alert(t.getMessage());
         }

         public void onSuccess(Object data) {
            Window.alert((String) data);
         }         
      });      
   }
   
   ...]]></programlisting>
    
    
    <para>
      When clicked, the button invokes the <literal>askServer()</literal> method passing the contents of the input text (in this
      example, validation is also performed to ensure that the input is a valid question).  The <literal>askServer()</literal>
      method acquires a reference to the asynchronous client stub (returned by the <literal>getService()</literal> method)
      and invokes the <literal>askIt()</literal> method.  The result (or error message if the call fails) is shown in an alert window.      
    </para>
    
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="images/gwt-helloworld.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="images/gwt-helloworld.png" align="center"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>    
    
    
    <para>
      The complete code for this example can be found in the Seam distribution in the <literal>examples/remoting/gwt</literal>
      directory.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>GWT Ant Targets</title>
  
    <para>
      For deployment of GWT apps, there is a compile-to-Javascript step (which compacts and obfuscates the code).  There is an
      ant utility which can be used instead of the command line or GUI utility that GWT provides.  To use this, you will need
      to have the ant task jar in your ant classpath, as well as GWT downloaded (which you will need for hosted mode anyway).
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Then, in your ant file, place (near the top of your ant file):
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<taskdef uri="antlib:de.samaflost.gwttasks"
   resource="de/samaflost/gwttasks/antlib.xml"
   classpath="./lib/gwttasks.jar"/>
   
   <property file="build.properties"/>]]></programlisting>
  
    <para>
      Create a <literal>build.properties</literal> file, which has the contents:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting><![CDATA[gwt.home=/gwt_home_dir]]></programlisting>
    
    <para>
      This of course should point to the directory where GWT is installed.  Then to use it, create a target:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<!-- the following are are handy utilities for doing GWT development.
   To use GWT, you will of course need to download GWT seperately -->
   <target name="gwt-compile">
      <!-- in this case, we are "re homing" the gwt generated stuff, so in this case
      we can only have one GWT module - we are doing this deliberately to keep the URL short -->
      <delete>
         <fileset dir="view"/>
      </delete>
      <gwt:compile outDir="build/gwt"
         gwtHome="${gwt.home}"
         classBase="${gwt.module.name}"
         sourceclasspath="src"/>
      <copy todir="view">
         <fileset dir="build/gwt/${gwt.module.name}"/>
      </copy>
   </target>]]></programlisting>
  
    <para>
      This target when called will compile the GWT application, and copy it to the specified directory (which would be
      in the <literal>webapp</literal> part of your war - remember GWT generates HTML and Javascript artifacts).  You
      never edit the resulting code that <literal>gwt-compile</literal> generates - you always edit in the GWT source
      directory.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Remember that GWT comes with a hosted mode browser - you should be using that if you are developing with GWT.  If you
      aren't using that, and are just compiling it each time, you aren't getting the most out of the toolkit (in fact, if
      you can't or won't use the hosted mode browser, I would go far as to say you should NOT be using GWT at all - it's
      that valuable!).
    </para>
    
  </section>
</chapter>
