<chapter id="jbpm">
    <title>Pageflows and business processes</title>
    
    <para>
        JBoss jBPM is a business process management engine for any Java SE or EE
        environment. jBPM lets you represent a business process or user 
        interaction as a graph of nodes representing wait states, decisions,
        tasks, web pages, etc. The graph is defined using a simple, very readable, 
        XML dialect called jPDL, and may be edited and visualised graphically using
        an eclipse plugin. jPDL is an extensible language, and is suitable for 
        a range of problems, from defining web application page flow, to traditional
        workflow management, all the way up to orchestration of services in a SOA
        environment.
    </para>
    
    <para>
        Seam applications use jBPM for two different problems:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
        <para>
            Defining the pageflow involved in complex user interactions. A jPDL
            process definition defines the page flow for a single conversation.
            A Seam conversation is considered to be a relatively short-running
            interaction with a single user.
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
            Defining the overarching business process. The business process may span
            multiple conversations with multiple users. Its state is persistent in
            the jBPM database, so it is considered long-running. Coordination of
            the activities of multiple users is a much more complex problem than
            scripting an interaction with a single user, so jBPM offers sophisticated
            facilities for task management and dealing with multiple concurrent paths 
            of execution.
        </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>
        Don't get these two things confused! They operate at very different levels
        or granularity. <emphasis>Pageflow</emphasis>, <emphasis>conversation</emphasis>
        and <emphasis>task</emphasis> all refer to a single
        interaction with a single user. A business process spans many tasks.
        Futhermore, the two applications of jBPM are totally orthogonal. You can
        use them together or independently or not at all.
    </para>
    
    <para>
        You don't have to know jDPL to use Seam. If you're perfectly happy defining
        pageflow using JSF or Seam navigation rules, and if your application is more 
        data-driven that process-driven, you probably don't need jBPM. But we're
        finding that thinking of user interaction in terms of a well-defined graphical 
        representation is helping us build more robust applications.
    </para>
    
    <section>
        <title>Pageflow in Seam</title>
        <para>
            There are two ways to define pageflow in Seam:
        </para>
        
	    <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	        <para>
	            Using JSF or Seam navigation rules - the <emphasis>stateless navigation 
	            model</emphasis>
	        </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	        <para>
	            Using jPDL - the <emphasis>stateful navigation model</emphasis>
	        </para>
	        </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
    
        <para>
            Very simple applications will only need the stateless navigation 
            model. Very complex applications will use both models in different 
            places. Each model has its strengths and weaknesses!
        </para>
        
        <section>
            <title>The two navigation models</title>
        
        <para>
            The stateless model defines a mapping from a set of named, logical
            outcomes of an event directly to the resulting page of the view.
            The navigation rules are entirely oblivious to any state held by
            the application other than what page was the source of the event.
            This means that your action listener methods must sometimes make 
            decisions about the page flow, since only they have access to the 
            current state of the application. 
        </para>
        
        <para>
            Here is an example page flow definition using JSF navigation 
            rules:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<navigation-rule>
    <from-view-id>/numberGuess.jsp</from-view-id>
        
    <navigation-case>
        <from-outcome>guess</from-outcome>
        <to-view-id>/numberGuess.jsp</to-view-id>
        <redirect/>
    </navigation-case>

    <navigation-case>
        <from-outcome>win</from-outcome>
        <to-view-id>/win.jsp</to-view-id>
        <redirect/>
    </navigation-case>
        
    <navigation-case>
        <from-outcome>lose</from-outcome>
        <to-view-id>/lose.jsp</to-view-id>
        <redirect/>
    </navigation-case>

</navigation-rule>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Here is the same example page flow definition using Seam navigation 
            rules:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page view-id="/numberGuess.jsp">
        
    <navigation>
        <rule if-outcome="guess">
            <redirect view-id="/numberGuess.jsp"/>
        </rule>
        <rule if-outcome="win">
            <redirect view-id="/win.jsp"/>
        </rule>
        <rule if-outcome="lose">
            <redirect view-id="/lose.jsp"/>
        </rule>
    </navigation>

</page>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            If you find navigation rules overly verbose, you can return view ids
            directly from your action listener methods:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public String guess() {
    if (guess==randomNumber) return "/win.jsp";
    if (++guessCount==maxGuesses) return "/lose.jsp";
    return null;
}]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Note that this results in a redirect. You can even specify parameters 
            to be used in the redirect:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public String search() {
    return "/searchResults.jsp?searchPattern=#{searchAction.searchPattern}";
}]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
            The stateful model defines a set of transitions between a set of
            named, logical application states. In this model, it is possible
            to express the flow of any user interaction entirely in the jPDL
            pageflow definition, and write action listener methods that are
            completely unaware of the flow of the interaction.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            Here is an example page flow definition using jPDL:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<pageflow-definition name="numberGuess">
    
   <start-page name="displayGuess" view-id="/numberGuess.jsp">
      <redirect/>
      <transition name="guess" to="evaluateGuess">
      	<action expression="#{numberGuess.guess}" />
      </transition>
   </start-page>
   
   <decision name="evaluateGuess" expression="#{numberGuess.correctGuess}">
      <transition name="true" to="win"/>
      <transition name="false" to="evaluateRemainingGuesses"/>
   </decision>
   
   <decision name="evaluateRemainingGuesses" expression="#{numberGuess.lastGuess}">
      <transition name="true" to="lose"/>
      <transition name="false" to="displayGuess"/>
   </decision>
   
   <page name="win" view-id="/win.jsp">
      <redirect/>
      <end-conversation />
   </page>
   
   <page name="lose" view-id="/lose.jsp">
      <redirect/>
      <end-conversation />
   </page>
   
</pageflow-definition>]]></programlisting>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="images/plugin-jbpm-numguess.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="images/plugin-jbpm-numguess.png" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        
        <para>
            There are two things we notice immediately here:
        </para>
	    
	    <itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	        <para>
	            The JSF/Seam navigation rules are <emphasis>much</emphasis> simpler.
	            (However, this obscures the fact that the underlying Java code
	            is more complex.)
	        </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	        <para>
	            The jPDL makes the user interaction immediately understandable,
	            without us needing to even look at the JSP or Java code.
	        </para>
	        </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	    
	    <para>
	        In addition, the stateful model is more <emphasis>constrained</emphasis>.
	        For each logical state (each step in the page flow), there are a 
	        constrained set of possible transitions to other states. The stateless
	        model is an <emphasis>ad hoc</emphasis> model which is suitable to 
	        relatively unconstrained, freeform navigation where the user decides
	        where he/she wants to go next, not the application.
	    </para>
	    
	    <para>
	        The stateful/stateless navigation distinction is quite similar to
	        the traditional view of modal/modeless interaction. Now, Seam 
	        applications are not usually modal in the simple sense of the 
	        word - indeed, avoiding application modal behavior is one of the
	        main reasons for having conversations! However, Seam applications
	        can be, and often are, modal at the level of a particular 
	        conversation. It is well-known that modal behavior is something
	        to avoid as much as possible; it is very difficult to predict the
	        order in which your users are going to want to do things! However,
	        there is no doubt that the stateful model has its place.
	    </para>
	    
	    <para>
	        The biggest contrast between the two models is the back-button
	        behavior.
	    </para>
	    
	    </section>
	    
	    <section>
	        <title>Seam and the back button</title>
	    
	    <para>
	        When JSF or Seam navigation rules are used, Seam lets the user freely 
	        navigate via the back, forward and refresh buttons. It is the
	        responsibility of the application to ensure that conversational
	        state remains internally consistent when this occurs. Experience
	        with the combination of web application frameworks like Struts 
	        or WebWork - that do not support a conversational model - and 
	        stateless component models like EJB stateless session beans 
	        or the Spring framework has taught many developers that this is
	        close to impossible to do! However, our experience is that in 
	        the context of Seam, where there is a well-defined conversational
	        model, backed by stateful session beans, it is actually quite 
	        straightforward. Usually it is as simple as combining the use 
	        of <literal>no-conversation-view-id</literal> with null 
	        checks at the beginning of action listener methods. We consider
	        support for freeform navigation to be almost always desirable.
	    </para>
	    
	    <para>
	        In this case, the <literal>no-conversation-view-id</literal> 
	        declaration goes in <literal>pages.xml</literal>. It tells
	        Seam to redirect to a different page if a request originates
	        from a page rendered during a conversation, and that conversation
	        no longer exists:
	    </para>
	    
	    <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page view-id="/checkout.xhtml" 
        no-conversation-view-id="/main.xhtml"/>]]></programlisting>
	    
	    <para>
	        On the other hand, in the stateful model, using the back button is 
	        interpreted as an undefined transition back to a previous state.
	        Since the stateful model enforces a defined set of transitions
	        from the current state, the back button is not permitted by default
	        in the stateful model! Seam transparently detects the use of the
	        back button, and blocks any attempt to perform an action from
	        a previous, "stale" page, and simply redirects the user to 
	        the "current" page (and displays a faces message). Whether you 
	        consider this a feature or a limitation of the stateful model 
	        depends upon your point of view: as an application developer, 
	        it is a feature; as a user, it might be frustrating! You can
	        enable backbutton navigation from a particular page node by
	        setting <literal>back="enabled"</literal>.
	    </para>
	    
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page name="checkout" 
        view-id="/checkout.xhtml" 
        back="enabled">
    <redirect/>
    <transition to="checkout"/>
    <transition name="complete" to="complete"/>
</page>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            This allows navigation via the back button <emphasis>from</emphasis>
            the <literal>checkout</literal> state to <emphasis>any previous
            state!</emphasis>
        </para>

        <note>
           If a page is set to redirect after a transition, it is not possible
           to use the back button to return to that page even when back is
           enabled on a page later in the flow. The reason is because Seam
           stores information about the pageflow in the page scope and the back
           button must result in a POST for that information to be restored
           (i.e., a Faces request). A redirect severs this linkage.
        </note>
        
        <para>
            Of course, we still need to define what happens if a request 
            originates from a page rendered during a pageflow, and the
            conversation with the pageflow no longer exists. In this case,
            the <literal>no-conversation-view-id</literal> declaration
            goes into the pageflow definition:
        </para>

        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page name="checkout" 
        view-id="/checkout.xhtml" 
        back="enabled" 
        no-conversation-view-id="/main.xhtml">
    <redirect/>
    <transition to="checkout"/>
    <transition name="complete" to="complete"/>
</page>]]></programlisting>


    	    <para>
	        In practice, both navigation models have their place, and you'll 
	        quickly learn to recognize when to prefer one model over the other.
	        </para>

        </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Using jPDL pageflows</title>
        
        <section>
            <title>Installing pageflows</title>
            
        <para>
            We need to install the Seam jBPM-related components, and place the
            pageflow definitions (using the standard <literal>.jpdl.xml</literal>
            extension) inside a Seam archive (an archive which 
            contains a <literal>seam.properties</literal> file):
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<bpm:jbpm />]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
            We can also explicitly tell Seam where to find our pageflow 
            definition. We specify this in <literal>components.xml</literal>:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<bpm:jbpm>
    <bpm:pageflow-definitions>
        <value>pageflow.jpdl.xml</value>
    </bpm:pageflow-definitions>
</bpm:jbpm>]]></programlisting>
        
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Starting pageflows</title>
        
        <para>
            We "start" a jPDL-based pageflow by specifying the name of the
            process definition using a <literal>@Begin</literal>,
            <literal>@BeginTask</literal> or <literal>@StartTask</literal> 
            annotation:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Begin(pageflow="numberguess")
public void begin() { ... }]]></programlisting>

		<para>Alternatively we can start a pageflow using pages.xml:</para>
		
		<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page>
        <begin-conversation pageflow="numberguess"/>
    </page>]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
            If we are beginning the pageflow during the <literal>RENDER_RESPONSE</literal>
            phase &#8212; during a <literal>@Factory</literal> or <literal>@Create</literal>
            method, for example &#8212; we consider ourselves to be already at the page being 
            rendered, and use  a <literal>&lt;start-page&gt;</literal> node as the first node 
            in the pageflow, as in the example above.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            But if the pageflow is begun as the result of an action listener invocation,
            the outcome of the action listener determines which is the first page to be
            rendered. In this case, we use a <literal>&lt;start-state&gt;</literal> as
            the first node in the pageflow, and declare a transition for each possible
            outcome:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<pageflow-definition name="viewEditDocument">

    <start-state name="start">
        <transition name="documentFound" to="displayDocument"/>
        <transition name="documentNotFound" to="notFound"/>
    </start-state>
    
    <page name="displayDocument" view-id="/document.jsp">
        <transition name="edit" to="editDocument"/>
        <transition name="done" to="main"/>
    </page>
    
    ...
    
    <page name="notFound" view-id="/404.jsp">
        <end-conversation/>
    </page>
    
</pageflow-definition>]]></programlisting>

        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Page nodes and transitions</title>

        <para>
            Each <literal>&lt;page&gt;</literal> node represents a state where
            the system is waiting for user input:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page name="displayGuess" view-id="/numberGuess.jsp">
    <redirect/>
    <transition name="guess" to="evaluateGuess">
        <action expression="#{numberGuess.guess}" />
    </transition>
</page>]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
            The <literal>view-id</literal> is the JSF view id. The <literal>&lt;redirect/&gt;</literal>
            element has the same effect as <literal>&lt;redirect/&gt;</literal> in a 
            JSF navigation rule: namely, a post-then-redirect behavior, to overcome problems
            with the browser's refresh button. (Note that Seam propagates conversation contexts
            over these browser redirects. So there is no need for a Ruby on Rails style "flash"
            construct in Seam!)
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The transition name is the name of a JSF outcome triggered by clicking
            a command button or command link in <literal>numberGuess.jsp</literal>. 
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<h:commandButton type="submit" value="Guess" action="guess"/>]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
            When the transition is triggered by clicking this button, jBPM will activate the
            transition action by calling the <literal>guess()</literal> method of the
            <literal>numberGuess</literal> component. Notice that the syntax used for
            specifying actions in the jPDL is just a familiar JSF EL expression, and that 
            the transition action handler is just a method of a Seam component in the
            current Seam contexts. So we have exactly the same event model for jBPM events 
            that we already have for JSF events! (The <emphasis>One Kind of Stuff</emphasis> 
            principle.)
        </para>
        
        <para>
            In the case of a null outcome (for example, a command button with no 
            <literal>action</literal> defined), Seam will signal the transition with no
            name if one exists, or else simply redisplay the page if all transitions
            have names. So we could slightly simplify our example pageflow and this button:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<h:commandButton type="submit" value="Guess"/>]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>
            Would fire the following un-named transition:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page name="displayGuess" view-id="/numberGuess.jsp">
    <redirect/>
    <transition to="evaluateGuess">
        <action expression="#{numberGuess.guess}" />
    </transition>
</page>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            It is even possible to have the button call an action method, in which case the
            action outcome will determine the transition to be taken:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<h:commandButton type="submit" value="Guess" action="#{numberGuess.guess}"/>]]></programlisting>
        
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page name="displayGuess" view-id="/numberGuess.jsp">
    <transition name="correctGuess" to="win"/>
    <transition name="incorrectGuess" to="evaluateGuess"/>
</page>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            However, this is considered an inferior style, since it moves responsibility for
            controlling the flow out of the pageflow definition and back into the other
            components. It is much better to centralize this concern in the pageflow itself.
        </para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Controlling the flow</title>

        <para>
            Usually, we don't need the more powerful features of jPDL when defining pageflows. 
            We do need the <literal>&lt;decision&gt;</literal> node, however:
        </para>
        
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<decision name="evaluateGuess" expression="#{numberGuess.correctGuess}">
    <transition name="true" to="win"/>
    <transition name="false" to="evaluateRemainingGuesses"/>
</decision>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            A decision is made by evaluating a JSF EL expression in the Seam contexts.
        </para>
        
        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Ending the flow</title>
   
        <para>
            We end the conversation using <literal>&lt;end-conversation&gt;</literal>
            or <literal>@End</literal>. (In fact, for readability, use of 
            <emphasis>both</emphasis> is encouraged.)
        </para>
        
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page name="win" view-id="/win.jsp">
    <redirect/>
    <end-conversation/>
</page>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Optionally, we can end a task, specify a jBPM <literal>transition</literal> 
            name. In this case, Seam will signal the end of the current task in the 
            overarching business process.
        </para>
        
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page name="win" view-id="/win.jsp">
    <redirect/>
    <end-task transition="success"/>
</page>]]></programlisting>

        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Pageflow composition</title>
            <para>
                It is possible to compose pageflows and have one pageflow pause 
                pause while another pageflow executes. The <literal>&lt;process-state&gt;</literal>
                node pauses the outer pageflow, and begins execution of a named 
                pageflow:
            </para>
            
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<process-state name="cheat">
    <sub-process name="cheat"/>
    <transition to="displayGuess"/>
</process-state>]]></programlisting>

            <para>
                The inner flow begins executing at a <literal>&lt;start-state&gt;</literal>
                node. When it reaches an <literal>&lt;end-state&gt;</literal> node, 
                execution of the inner flow ends, and execution of the outer flow
                resumes with the transition defined by the <literal>&lt;process-state&gt;</literal>
                element.
            </para>
            
        </section>

    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>Business process management in Seam</title>
        <para>
            A business process is a well-defined set of tasks that must
            be performed by users or software systems according to 
            well-defined rules about <emphasis>who</emphasis> can perform 
            a task, and <emphasis>when</emphasis> it should be performed.
            Seam's jBPM integration makes it easy to display lists of
            tasks to users and let them manage their tasks. Seam also
            lets the application store state associated with the business
            process in the <literal>BUSINESS_PROCESS</literal> context,
            and have that state made persistent via jBPM variables.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            A simple business process definition looks much the same as a 
            page flow definition (<emphasis>One Kind of Stuff</emphasis>), 
            except that instead of <literal>&lt;page&gt;</literal> nodes,
            we have <literal>&lt;task-node&gt;</literal> nodes. In a 
            long-running business process, the wait states are where the
            system is waiting for some user to log in and perform a task.
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<process-definition name="todo">
   
   <start-state name="start">
      <transition to="todo"/>
   </start-state>
   
   <task-node name="todo">
      <task name="todo" description="#{todoList.description}">
         <assignment actor-id="#{actor.id}"/>
      </task>
      <transition to="done"/>
   </task-node>
   
   <end-state name="done"/>
   
</process-definition>]]></programlisting>

        
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="images/plugin-jbpm-todo.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="images/plugin-jbpm-todo.png" align="center"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        
        <para>
            It is perfectly possible that we might have both jPDL business 
            process definitions and jPDL pageflow definitions in the
            same project. If so, the relationship between the two is that
            a single <literal>&lt;task&gt;</literal> in a business process
            corresponds to a whole pageflow 
            <literal>&lt;pageflow-definition&gt;</literal>
        </para>
        </section>
    
        <section>
            <title>Using jPDL business process definitions</title>
        
        <section>
            <title>Installing process definitions</title>
        
        <para>
            We need to install jBPM, and tell it where to find the
            business process definitions:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<bpm:jbpm>
    <bpm:process-definitions>
        <value>todo.jpdl.xml</value>
    </bpm:process-definitions>
</bpm:jbpm>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            As jBPM processes are persistent across application restarts, 
            when using Seam in a production environment you won't want to
            install the process definition every time the application starts.
            Therefore, in a production environment, you'll need to deploy
            the process to jBPM outside of Seam. In other words, only install
            process definitions from <literal>components.xml</literal> when
            developing your application.
        </para>

        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Initializing actor ids</title>
        
        <para>
            We always need to know what user is currently logged in.
            jBPM "knows" users by their <emphasis>actor id</emphasis>
            and <emphasis>group actor ids</emphasis>. We specify the
            current actor ids using the built in Seam component named
            <literal>actor</literal>:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@In Actor actor;

public String login() {
    ...
    actor.setId( user.getUserName() );
    actor.getGroupActorIds().addAll( user.getGroupNames() );
    ...
}]]></programlisting>

        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Initiating a business process</title>
        
        <para>
            To initiate a business process instance, we use the 
            <literal>@CreateProcess</literal> annotation:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@CreateProcess(definition="todo")
public void createTodo() { ... }]]></programlisting>

        <para>Alternatively we can initiate a business process using pages.xml:</para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page>
    <create-process definition="todo" />
</page>]]></programlisting>

        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Task assignment</title>
        
        <para>
            When a process reaches a task node, task instances are created. These must be 
            assigned to users or user groups. We can either hardcode our actor ids, or 
            delegate to a Seam component:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<task name="todo" description="#{todoList.description}">
    <assignment actor-id="#{actor.id}"/>
</task>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            In this case, we have simply assigned the task to the current user. 
            We can also assign tasks to a pool:
        </para>

        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<task name="todo" description="#{todoList.description}">
    <assignment pooled-actors="employees"/>
</task>]]></programlisting>

        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Task lists</title>

        <para>
            Several built-in Seam components make it easy to display task lists. 
            The <literal>pooledTaskInstanceList</literal> is a list of pooled tasks 
            that users may assign to themselves:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<h:dataTable value="#{pooledTaskInstanceList}" var="task">
    <h:column>
        <f:facet name="header">Description</f:facet>
        <h:outputText value="#{task.description}"/>
    </h:column>
    <h:column>
        <s:link action="#{pooledTask.assignToCurrentActor}" value="Assign" taskInstance="#{task}"/>
    </h:column>            	
</h:dataTable>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            Note that instead of <literal>&lt;s:link&gt;</literal> we could have used
            a plain JSF <literal>&lt;h:commandLink&gt;</literal>:
        </para>

        <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<h:commandLink action="#{pooledTask.assignToCurrentActor}"> 
    <f:param name="taskId" value="#{task.id}"/>
</h:commandLink>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            The <literal>pooledTask</literal> component is a built-in component that
            simply assigns the task to the current user.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            The <literal>taskInstanceListForType</literal> component includes tasks of 
            a particular type that are assigned to the current user:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<h:dataTable value="#{taskInstanceListForType['todo']}" var="task">
    <h:column>
        <f:facet name="header">Description</f:facet>
        <h:outputText value="#{task.description}"/>
    </h:column>
    <h:column>
        <s:link action="#{todoList.start}" value="Start Work" taskInstance="#{task}"/>
    </h:column>            	
</h:dataTable>]]></programlisting>

        </section>
        
        <section>
            <title>Performing a task</title>
        
        <para>
            To begin work on a task, we use either <literal>@StartTask</literal>
            or <literal>@BeginTask</literal> on the listener method:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@StartTask
public String start() { ... }]]></programlisting>

        <para>Alternatively we can begin work on a task using pages.xml:</para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page>
    <start-task />
</page>]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>    
            These annotations begin a special kind of conversation that has 
            significance in terms of the overarching business process. Work done 
            by this conversation has access to state held in the business
            process context.
        </para>
        
        <para>
            If we end the conversation using <literal>@EndTask</literal>, Seam
            will signal the completion of the task:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@EndTask(transition="completed")
public String completed() { ... }]]></programlisting>

        <para>Alternatively we can use pages.xml:</para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<page>
    <end-task transition="completed" />
</page>]]></programlisting>

        <para>
            You can also use EL to specify the transition in pages.xml.
        </para>

        <para>
            At this point, jBPM takes over and continues executing the business process
            definition. (In more complex processes, several tasks might need to be
            completed before process execution can resume.)
        </para>                
        
            <para>
            Please refer to the jBPM documentation for a more thorough overview of 
            the sophisticated features that jBPM provides for managing complex
            business processes.
            </para>

        </section>
    </section>
    
</chapter>
