<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>


<preface id="Book-Preface">
        <title>Introduction to JBoss Seam</title>

        <para>
            Seam is an application framework for Enterprise Java. It is inspired by the following principles:
        </para>

        <variablelist>
        
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>One kind of "stuff"</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Seam defines a uniform component model for all business logic in your application. 
                        A Seam component may be stateful, with the state associated with any one of several
                        well-defined contexts, including the long-running, persistent, <emphasis>business process 
                        context</emphasis> and the <emphasis>conversation context</emphasis>, which is
                        preserved across multiple web requests in a user interaction.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        There is no distinction between presentation tier components and business logic
                        components in Seam. You can layer your application according to whatever architecture
                        you devise, rather than being forced to shoehorn your application logic into an
                        unnatural layering scheme forced upon you by whatever combination of stovepipe 
                        frameworks you're using today.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Unlike plain Java EE or J2EE components, Seam components may <emphasis>simultaneously</emphasis>
                        access state associated with the web request and state held in transactional resources (without
                        the need to propagate web request state manually via method parameters). You might object
                        that the application layering imposed upon you by the old J2EE platform was a Good Thing.
                        Well, nothing stops you creating an equivalent layered architecture using Seam &#8212; the difference
                        is that <emphasis>you</emphasis> get to architect your own application and decide what the
                        layers are and how they work together.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>Integrate JSF with EJB 3.0</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        JSF and EJB 3.0 are two of the best new features of Java EE 5. EJB3 is a brand new
                        component model for server side business and persistence logic. Meanwhile, JSF is a
                        great component model for the presentation tier. Unfortunately, neither component
                        model is able to solve all problems in computing by itself. Indeed, JSF and EJB3
                        work best used together. But the Java EE 5 specification provides no standard way
                        to integrate the two component models. Fortunately, the creators of both models
                        foresaw this situation and provided standard extension points to allow extension
                        and integration with other frameworks.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Seam unifies the component models of JSF and EJB3, eliminating glue code, and letting
                        the developer think about the business problem.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        It is possible to write Seam applications where "everything" is an EJB. This may come 
                        as a surprise if you're used to thinking of EJBs as coarse-grained, so-called 
                        "heavyweight" objects. However, version 3.0 has completely changed the nature of EJB 
                        from the point of view of the developer. An EJB is a fine-grained object &#8212; nothing 
                        more complex than an annotated JavaBean. Seam even encourages you to use session beans 
                        as JSF action listeners!                    
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        On the other hand, if you prefer not to adopt EJB 3.0 at this time, you don't have to.
                        Virtually any Java class may be a Seam component, and Seam provides all the functionality
                        that you expect from a "lightweight" container, and more, for any component, EJB or 
                        otherwise.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>Integrated AJAX</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Seam supports the best open source JSF-based AJAX solutions: JBoss RichFaces and 
                        ICEfaces. These solutions let you add AJAX capability to your user interface without 
                        the need to write any JavaScript code.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Alternatively, Seam provides a built-in JavaScript remoting layer that lets you call 
                        components asynchronously from client-side JavaScript without the need for an intermediate 
                        action layer. You can even subscribe to server-side JMS topics and receive messages via AJAX
                        push.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Neither of these approaches would work well, were it not for Seam's built-in concurrency 
                        and state management, which ensures that many concurrent fine-grained, asynchronous AJAX 
                        requests are handled safely and efficiently on the server side.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>Business process as a first class construct</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Optionally, Seam provides transparent business process management via jBPM. You won't 
                        believe how easy it is to implement complex workflows, collaboration and and task management 
                        using jBPM and Seam.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Seam even allows you to define presentation tier pageflow using the same language (jPDL)
                        that jBPM uses for business process definition.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        JSF provides an incredibly rich event model for the presentation tier. Seam enhances this
                        model by exposing jBPM's business process related events via exactly the same event handling
                        mechanism, providing a uniform event model for Seam's uniform component model.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>Declarative state management</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        We're all used to the concept of declarative transaction management and declarative
                        security from the early days of EJB. EJB 3.0 even introduces declarative persistence context
                        management. These are three examples of a broader problem of managing state that is
                        associated with a particular <emphasis>context</emphasis>, while ensuring that all needed
                        cleanup occurs when the context ends. Seam takes the concept of declarative state
                        management much further and applies it to <emphasis>application state</emphasis>.
                        Traditionally, J2EE applications implement state management manually, by getting
                        and setting servlet session and request attributes. This approach to state management is the
                        source of many bugs and memory leaks when applications fail to clean up session attributes,
                        or when session data associated with different workflows collides in a multi-window
                        application. Seam has the potential to almost entirely eliminate this class of bugs.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Declarative application state management is made possible by the richness of the
                        <emphasis>context model</emphasis> defined by Seam. Seam extends the context model defined 
                        by the servlet spec &#8212; request, session, application &#8212; with two new
                        contexts &#8212; conversation and business process &#8212; that are more meaningful from the
                        point of view of the business logic.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        You'll be amazed at how many things become easier once you start using conversations.
                        Have you ever suffered pain dealing with lazy association fetching in an ORM solution
                        like Hibernate or JPA? Seam's conversation-scoped persistence contexts mean you'll
                        rarely have to see a <literal>LazyInitializationException</literal>. Have you ever
                        had problems with the refresh button? The back button? With duplicate form submission?
                        With propagating messages across a post-then-redirect? Seam's conversation management 
                        solves these problems without you even needing to really think about them. They're all
                        symptoms of the broken state management architecture that has been prevalent since the 
                        earliest days of the web.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>Bijection</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The notion of <emphasis>Inversion of Control</emphasis> or <emphasis>dependency injection</emphasis>
                        exists in both JSF and EJB3, as well as in numerous so-called "lightweight containers". Most of
                        these containers emphasize injection of components that implement <emphasis>stateless services</emphasis>.
                        Even when injection of stateful components is supported (such as in JSF), it is virtually useless
                        for handling application state because the scope of the stateful component cannot be defined with
                        sufficient flexibility, and because components belonging to wider scopes may not be injected into 
                        components belonging to narrower scopes.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        <emphasis>Bijection</emphasis> differs from IoC in that it is <emphasis>dynamic</emphasis>, 
                        <emphasis>contextual</emphasis>, and <emphasis>bidirectional</emphasis>.
                        You can think of it as a mechanism for aliasing contextual variables (names in the various contexts
                        bound to the current thread) to attributes of the component. Bijection allows auto-assembly of stateful
                        components by the container. It even allows a component to safely and easily manipulate the
                        value of a context variable, just by assigning it to an attribute of the component.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>Workspace management and multi-window browsing</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Seam applications let the user freely switch between multiple browser tabs, each associated with a
                        different, safely isolated, conversation. Applications may even take advantage of <emphasis>workspace 
                        management</emphasis>, allowing the user to switch between conversations (workspaces) in a single
                        browser tab. Seam provides not only correct multi-window operation, but also multi-window-like
                        operation in a single window!
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>Prefer annotations to XML</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Traditionally, the Java community has been in a state of deep confusion about precisely 
                        what kinds of meta-information counts as configuration. J2EE and popular "lightweight"
                        containers have provided XML-based deployment descriptors both for things which are
                        truly configurable between different deployments of the system, and for any other kinds
                        or declaration which can not easily be expressed in Java. Java 5 annotations changed
                        all this.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        EJB 3.0 embraces annotations and "configuration by exception" as the easiest way to provide
                        information to the container in a declarative form. Unfortunately, JSF is still heavily
                        dependent on verbose XML configuration files. Seam extends the annotations provided by
                        EJB 3.0 with a set of annotations for declarative state management and declarative
                        context demarcation. This lets you eliminate the noisy JSF managed bean declarations
                        and reduce the required XML to just that information which truly belongs in XML
                        (the JSF navigation rules).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>Integration testing is easy</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Seam components, being plain Java classes, are by nature unit testable. But for complex applications,
                        unit testing alone is insufficient. Integration testing has traditionally been a messy and
                        difficult task for Java web applications. Therefore, Seam provides for testability of Seam
                        applications as a core feature of the framework. You can easily write JUnit or TestNG tests
                        that reproduce a whole interaction with a user, exercising all components of the system
                        apart from the view (the JSP or Facelets page). You can run these tests directly inside your
                        IDE, where Seam will automatically deploy EJB components using JBoss Embedded.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>The specs ain't perfect</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        We think the latest incarnation of Java EE is great. But we know it's never going to be 
                        perfect. Where there are holes in the specifications (for example, limitations in the
                        JSF lifecycle for GET requests), Seam fixes them. And the authors of Seam are working
                        with the JCP expert groups to make sure those fixes make their way back into the next
                        revision of the standards.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            
            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>There's more to a web application than serving HTML pages</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Today's web frameworks think too small. They let you get user input off a form and
                        into your Java objects. And then they leave you hanging. A truly complete web application
                        framework should address problems like persistence, concurrency, asynchronicity, state 
                        management, security, email, messaging, PDF and chart generation, workflow, wikitext
                        rendering, webservices, caching and more. Once you scratch the surface of Seam, you'll
                        be amazed at how many problems become simpler...
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Seam integrates JPA and Hibernate3 for persistence, the EJB Timer Service and Quartz 
                        for lightweight asychronicity, jBPM for workflow, JBoss Rules for business rules, Meldware 
                        Mail for email, Hibernate Search and Lucene for full text search, JMS for messaging and JBoss 
                        Cache for page fragment caching. Seam layers an innovative rule-based security framework over
                        JAAS and JBoss Rules. There's even JSF tag libraries for rendering PDF, outgoing email, charts 
                        and wikitext. Seam components may be called synchronously as a Web Service, asynchronously 
                        from client-side JavaScript or Google Web Toolkit or, of course, directly from JSF.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis>Get started now!</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Seam works in any Java EE application server, and even works in Tomcat. If your environment
                        supports EJB 3.0, great! If it doesn't, no problem, you can use Seam's built-in transaction
                        management with JPA or Hibernate3 for persistence. Or, you can deploy JBoss Embedded in
                        Tomcat, and get full support for EJB 3.0.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/architecture.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>
            It turns out that the combination of Seam, JSF and EJB3 is <emphasis>the</emphasis> simplest way
            to write a complex web application in Java. You won't believe how little code is required!
        </para>

	<xi:include href="Feedback.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    </preface>
