<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="remoting">
  <title>Remoting</title>
  <para> Seam provides a convenient method of remotely accessing components from a web page, using AJAX (Asynchronous
    Javascript and XML). The framework for this functionality is provided with almost no up-front development effort -
    your components only require simple annotating to become accessible via AJAX. This chapter describes the steps
    required to build an AJAX-enabled web page, then goes on to explain the features of the Seam Remoting framework in
    more detail. </para>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para> To use remoting, the Seam Resource servlet must first be configured in your <literal>web.xml</literal> file: </para>

    <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<servlet>
  <servlet-name>Seam Resource Servlet</servlet-name>
  <servlet-class>org.jboss.seam.servlet.SeamResourceServlet</servlet-class>
</servlet>

<servlet-mapping>
  <servlet-name>Seam Resource Servlet</servlet-name>
  <url-pattern>/seam/resource/*</url-pattern>
</servlet-mapping>]]></programlisting>

    <para> The next step is to import the necessary Javascript into your web page. There are a minimum of two scripts
      that must be imported. The first one contains all the client-side framework code that enables remoting
      functionality: </para>

    <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript" src="seam/resource/remoting/resource/remote.js"></script>]]></programlisting>

    <para> The second script contains the stubs and type definitions for the components you wish to call. It is
      generated dynamically based on the local interface of your components, and includes type definitions for all of
      the classes that can be used to call the remotable methods of the interface. The name of the script reflects the
      name of your component. For example, if you have a stateless session bean annotated with
        <literal>@Name("customerAction")</literal>, then your script tag should look like this: </para>

    <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript" 
          src="seam/resource/remoting/interface.js?customerAction"></script>]]></programlisting>

    <para> If you wish to access more than one component from the same page, then include them all as parameters of your
      script tag: </para>

    <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript" 
        src="seam/resource/remoting/interface.js?customerAction&accountAction"></script>]]></programlisting>
        
        
    <para>
      Alternatively, you may use the <literal>s:remote</literal> tag to import the required Javascript.  Separate each
      component or class name you wish to import with a comma: 
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[
  <s:remote include="customerAction,accountAction"/>    
    ]]></programlisting>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The "Seam" object</title>

    <para> Client-side interaction with your components is all performed via the <literal>Seam</literal> Javascript
      object. This object is defined in <literal>remote.js</literal>, and you'll be using it to make asynchronous calls
      against your component. It is split into two areas of functionality; <literal>Seam.Component</literal> contains
      methods for working with components and <literal>Seam.Remoting</literal> contains methods for executing remote
      requests. The easiest way to become familiar with this object is to start with a simple example. </para>

    <section>
      <title>A Hello World example</title>

      <para> Let's step through a simple example to see how the <literal>Seam</literal> object works. First of all,
        let's create a new Seam component called <literal>helloAction</literal>. </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Stateless
@Name("helloAction")
public class HelloAction implements HelloLocal {
    public String sayHello(String name) {
        return "Hello, " + name;
    }
}]]></programlisting>

      <para>You also need to create a local interface for our new component - take special note of the
          <literal>@WebRemote</literal> annotation, as it's required to make our method accessible via remoting:</para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Local
public interface HelloLocal {
  @WebRemote
  public String sayHello(String name);
}]]></programlisting>

      <para> That's all the server-side code we need to write.</para>

      <note>
         <para>If you are performing a persistence operation in the method marked <literal>@WebRemote</literal> you will
         also need to add a <literal>@Transactional</literal> annotation to the method. Otherwise, your method would
         execute outside of a transaction without this extra hint.That's because unlike a JSF request, Seam does not
         wrap the remoting request in a transaction automatically.</para>
      </note>
      
      <para>Now for our web page - create a new page and import the 
          <literal>helloAction</literal> component: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<s:remote include="helloAction"/>]]></programlisting>

      <para> To make this a fully interactive user experience, let's add a button to our page: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<button onclick="javascript:sayHello()">Say Hello</button>]]></programlisting>

      <para> We'll also need to add some more script to make our button actually do something when it's clicked: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript">
  //<![CDATA[

  function sayHello() {
    var name = prompt("What is your name?");
    Seam.Component.getInstance("helloAction").sayHello(name, sayHelloCallback);
  }

  function sayHelloCallback(result) {
    alert(result);
  }

   // ]]>]]&gt;<![CDATA[
</script>]]></programlisting>

      <para> We're done! Deploy your application and browse to your page. Click the button, and enter a name when
        prompted. A message box will display the hello message confirming that the call was successful. If you want to
        save some time, you'll find the full source code for this Hello World example in Seam's
          <literal>/examples/remoting/helloworld</literal> directory. </para>

      <para> So what does the code of our script actually do? Let's break it down into smaller pieces. To start with,
        you can see from the Javascript code listing that we have implemented two methods - the first method is
        responsible for prompting the user for their name and then making a remote request. Take a look at the following
        line: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML">Seam.Component.getInstance("helloAction").sayHello(name, sayHelloCallback);</programlisting>

      <para> The first section of this line, <literal>Seam.Component.getInstance("helloAction")</literal> returns a
        proxy, or "stub" for our <literal>helloAction</literal> component. We can invoke the methods of our component
        against this stub, which is exactly what happens with the remainder of the line: <literal>sayHello(name,
          sayHelloCallback);</literal>. </para>

      <para> What this line of code in its completeness does, is invoke the <literal>sayHello</literal> method of our
        component, passing in <literal>name</literal> as a parameter. The second parameter,
        <literal>sayHelloCallback</literal> isn't a parameter of our component's <literal>sayHello</literal> method,
        instead it tells the Seam Remoting framework that once it receives the response to our request, it should pass
        it to the <literal>sayHelloCallback</literal> Javascript method. This callback parameter is entirely optional,
        so feel free to leave it out if you're calling a method with a <literal>void</literal> return type or if you
        don't care about the result. </para>

      <para> The <literal>sayHelloCallback</literal> method, once receiving the response to our remote request then pops
        up an alert message displaying the result of our method call. </para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Seam.Component</title>

      <para> The <literal>Seam.Component</literal> Javascript object provides a number of client-side methods for
        working with your Seam components. The two main methods, <literal>newInstance()</literal> and
          <literal>getInstance()</literal> are documented in the following sections however their main difference is
        that <literal>newInstance()</literal> will always create a new instance of a component type, and
          <literal>getInstance()</literal> will return a singleton instance. </para>

      <section>
        <title>Seam.Component.newInstance()</title>
        <para> Use this method to create a new instance of an entity or Javabean component. The object returned by this
          method will have the same getter/setter methods as its server-side counterpart, or alternatively if you wish
          you can access its fields directly. Take the following Seam entity component for example: </para>

        <programlisting role="JAVA">@Name("customer")
@Entity
public class Customer implements Serializable
{
  private Integer customerId;
  private String firstName;
  private String lastName;
    
  @Column public Integer getCustomerId() { 
    return customerId; 
  }
    
  public void setCustomerId(Integer customerId} { 
    this.customerId = customerId; 
  }
  
  @Column public String getFirstName() { 
    return firstName; 
  }
  
  public void setFirstName(String firstName) {
    this.firstName = firstName; 
  }
  
  @Column public String getLastName() {
    return lastName;
  }
  
  public void setLastName(String lastName) {
    this.lastName = lastName;
  }
}</programlisting>

        <para> To create a client-side Customer you would write the following code: </para>

        <programlisting role="XHTML">var customer = Seam.Component.newInstance("customer");</programlisting>

        <para> Then from here you can set the fields of the customer object: </para>

        <programlisting role="XHTML">customer.setFirstName("John");
// Or you can set the fields directly
customer.lastName = "Smith";</programlisting>

      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Seam.Component.getInstance()</title>

        <para> The <literal>getInstance()</literal> method is used to get a reference to a Seam session bean component
          stub, which can then be used to remotely execute methods against your component. This method returns a
          singleton for the specified component, so calling it twice in a row with the same component name will return
          the same instance of the component. </para>

        <para> To continue our example from before, if we have created a new <literal>customer</literal> and we now wish
          to save it, we would pass it to the <literal>saveCustomer()</literal> method of our
          <literal>customerAction</literal> component: </para>

        <programlisting role="XHTML">Seam.Component.getInstance("customerAction").saveCustomer(customer);</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Seam.Component.getComponentName()</title>

        <para> Passing an object into this method will return its component name if it is a component, or
          <literal>null</literal> if it is not. </para>

        <programlisting role="XHTML">if (Seam.Component.getComponentName(instance) == "customer")
  alert("Customer");
else if (Seam.Component.getComponentName(instance) == "staff")
  alert("Staff member");</programlisting>
      </section>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Seam.Remoting</title>

      <para> Most of the client side functionality for Seam Remoting is contained within the
        <literal>Seam.Remoting</literal> object. While you shouldn't need to directly call most of its methods, there
        are a couple of important ones worth mentioning. </para>

      <section>
        <title>Seam.Remoting.createType()</title>

        <para> If your application contains or uses Javabean classes that aren't Seam components, you may need to create
          these types on the client side to pass as parameters into your component method. Use the
          <literal>createType()</literal> method to create an instance of your type. Pass in the fully qualified Java
          class name as a parameter: </para>

        <programlisting role="XHTML">var widget = Seam.Remoting.createType("com.acme.widgets.MyWidget");</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Seam.Remoting.getTypeName()</title>

        <para> This method is the equivalent of <literal>Seam.Component.getComponentName()</literal> but for
          non-component types. It will return the name of the type for an object instance, or <literal>null</literal> if
          the type is not known. The name is the fully qualified name of the type's Java class. </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Evaluating EL Expressions</title>
    
    <para>
      Seam Remoting also supports the evaluation of EL expressions, which provides another convenient method for retrieving
      data from the server.  Using the <literal>Seam.Remoting.eval()</literal> function, an EL expression can be remotely
      evaluated on the server and the resulting value returned to a client-side callback method.  This function accepts two
      parameters, the first being the EL expression to evaluate, and the second being the callback method to invoke with the
      value of the expression.  Here's an example:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[  function customersCallback(customers) {
    for (var i = 0; i < customers.length; i++) {
      alert("Got customer: " + customers[i].getName());
    }    
  }
    
  Seam.Remoting.eval("#{customers}", customersCallback);  
    ]]></programlisting>
    
    <para>
      In this example, the expression <literal>#{customers}</literal> is evaluated by Seam, and the value of the expression
      (in this case a list of Customer objects) is returned to the <literal>customersCallback()</literal> method.  It is 
      important to remember that the objects returned this way must have their types imported (via <literal>s:remote</literal>)
      to be able to work with them in Javascript.  So to work with a list of <literal>customer</literal> objects,
      it is required to import the <literal>customer</literal> type:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<s:remote include="customer"/>]]></programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Client Interfaces</title>

    <para> In the configuration section above, the interface, or "stub" for our component is imported into our page 
        either via <literal>seam/resource/remoting/interface.js</literal>: or using the <literal>s:remote</literal>
        tag:
    </para>

    <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript" 
        src="seam/resource/remoting/interface.js?customerAction"></script>]]></programlisting>
        
    <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<s:remote include="customerAction"/>]]></programlisting>

    <para> By including this script in our page, the interface definitions for our component, plus any other components
      or types that are required to execute the methods of our component are generated and made available for the
      remoting framework to use. </para>

    <para> There are two types of client stub that can be generated, "executable" stubs and "type" stubs. Executable
      stubs are behavioural, and are used to execute methods against your session bean components, while type stubs
      contain state and represent the types that can be passed in as parameters or returned as a result. </para>

    <para> The type of client stub that is generated depends on the type of your Seam component. If the component is a
      session bean, then an executable stub will be generated, otherwise if it's an entity or JavaBean, then a type stub
      will be generated. There is one exception to this rule; if your component is a JavaBean (ie it is not a session
      bean nor an entity bean) and any of its methods are annotated with @WebRemote, then an executable stub will be
      generated for it instead of a type stub. This allows you to use remoting to call methods of your JavaBean
      components in a non-EJB environment where you don't have access to session beans. </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Context</title>

    <para> The Seam Remoting Context contains additional information which is sent and received as part of a remoting
      request/response cycle. At this stage it only contains the conversation ID but may be expanded in the future. </para>

    <section>
      <title>Setting and reading the Conversation ID</title>


    <para> If you intend on using remote calls within the scope of a conversation then you need to be able to read or
      set the conversation ID in the Seam Remoting Context. To read the conversation ID after making a remote request
      call <literal>Seam.Remoting.getContext().getConversationId()</literal>. To set the conversation ID before making a
      request, call <literal>Seam.Remoting.getContext().setConversationId()</literal>. </para>

    <para> If the conversation ID hasn't been explicitly set with
        <literal>Seam.Remoting.getContext().setConversationId()</literal>, then it will be automatically assigned the
      first valid conversation ID that is returned by any remoting call. If you are working with multiple conversations
      within your page, then you may need to explicitly set the conversation ID before each call. If you are working
      with just a single conversation, then you don't need to do anything special. </para>
    </section>      
    <section>
      <title>Remote calls within the current conversation scope</title>
      
      <para> In some circumstances it may be required to make a remote call within the scope of the
        current view's conversation.  To do this, you must explicitly set the conversation ID to that
        of the view before making the remote call.  This small snippet of JavaScript will set the
        conversation ID that is used for remoting calls to the current view's conversation ID: </para>
        
      <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[Seam.Remoting.getContext().setConversationId( #{conversation.id} );]]></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Batch Requests</title>

    <para> Seam Remoting allows multiple component calls to be executed within a single request. It is recommended that
      this feature is used wherever it is appropriate to reduce network traffic. </para>

    <para> The method <literal>Seam.Remoting.startBatch()</literal> will start a new batch, and any component calls
      executed after starting a batch are queued, rather than being sent immediately. When all the desired component
      calls have been added to the batch, the <literal>Seam.Remoting.executeBatch()</literal> method will send a single
      request containing all of the queued calls to the server, where they will be executed in order. After the calls
      have been executed, a single response containining all return values will be returned to the client and the
      callback functions (if provided) triggered in the same order as execution. </para>

    <para> If you start a new batch via the <literal>startBatch()</literal> method but then decide you don't want to
      send it, the <literal>Seam.Remoting.cancelBatch()</literal> method will discard any calls that were queued and
      exit the batch mode. </para>

    <para> To see an example of a batch being used, take a look at <literal>/examples/remoting/chatroom</literal>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Working with Data types</title>

    <section>
      <title>Primitives / Basic Types</title>

      <para> This section describes the support for basic data types. On the server side these values are generally
        compatible with either their primitive type or their corresponding wrapper class. </para>

      <section>
        <title>String</title>

        <para> Simply use Javascript String objects when setting String parameter values. </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Number</title>

        <para> There is support for all number types supported by Java. On the client side, number values are always
          serialized as their String representation and then on the server side they are converted to the correct
          destination type. Conversion into either a primitive or wrapper type is supported for <literal>Byte</literal>,
            <literal>Double</literal>, <literal>Float</literal>, <literal>Integer</literal>, <literal>Long</literal> and
            <literal>Short</literal> types. </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Boolean</title>

        <para> Booleans are represented client side by Javascript Boolean values, and server side by a Java boolean.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JavaBeans</title>

      <para> In general these will be either Seam entity or JavaBean components, or some other non-component class. Use
        the appropriate method (either <literal>Seam.Component.newInstance()</literal> for Seam components or
          <literal>Seam.Remoting.createType()</literal> for everything else) to create a new instance of the object. </para>

      <para> It is important to note that only objects that are created by either of these two methods should be used as
        parameter values, where the parameter is not one of the other valid types mentioned anywhere else in this
        section. In some situations you may have a component method where the exact parameter type cannot be determined,
        such as: </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@Name("myAction")
public class MyAction implements MyActionLocal {
  public void doSomethingWithObject(Object obj) {
    // code
  }
}</programlisting>

      <para> In this case you might want to pass in an instance of your <literal>myWidget</literal> component, however
        the interface for <literal>myAction</literal> won't include <literal>myWidget</literal> as it is not directly
        referenced by any of its methods. To get around this, <literal>MyWidget</literal> needs to be explicitly
        imported: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML"><![CDATA[<s:remote include="myAction,myWidget"/>]]></programlisting>

      <para> This will then allow a <literal>myWidget</literal> object to be created with
          <literal>Seam.Component.newInstance("myWidget")</literal>, which can then be passed to
          <literal>myAction.doSomethingWithObject()</literal>. </para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Dates and Times</title>

      <para> Date values are serialized into a String representation that is accurate to the millisecond. On the client
        side, use a Javascript Date object to work with date values. On the server side, use any
        <literal>java.util.Date</literal> (or descendent, such as <literal>java.sql.Date</literal> or
          <literal>java.sql.Timestamp</literal> class. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Enums</title>

      <para> On the client side, enums are treated the same as Strings. When setting the value for an enum parameter,
        simply use the String representation of the enum. Take the following component as an example: </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@Name("paintAction")
public class paintAction implements paintLocal {
  public enum Color {red, green, blue, yellow, orange, purple};

  public void paint(Color color) {
    // code
  }    
} </programlisting>

      <para> To call the <literal>paint()</literal> method with the color <literal>red</literal>, pass the parameter
        value as a String literal: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML">Seam.Component.getInstance("paintAction").paint("red");</programlisting>

      <para> The inverse is also true - that is, if a component method returns an enum parameter (or contains an enum
        field anywhere in the returned object graph) then on the client-side it will be represented as a String. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Collections</title>

      <section>
        <title>Bags</title>

        <para> Bags cover all collection types including arrays, collections, lists, sets, (but excluding Maps - see the
          next section for those), and are implemented client-side as a Javascript array. When calling a component
          method that accepts one of these types as a parameter, your parameter should be a Javascript array. If a
          component method returns one of these types, then the return value will also be a Javascript array. The
          remoting framework is clever enough on the server side to convert the bag to an appropriate type for the
          component method call. </para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Maps</title>

        <para> As there is no native support for Maps within Javascript, a simple Map implementation is provided with
          the Seam Remoting framework. To create a Map which can be used as a parameter to a remote call, create a new
            <literal>Seam.Remoting.Map</literal> object: </para>

        <programlisting role="XHTML">var map = new Seam.Remoting.Map();</programlisting>

        <para> This Javascript implementation provides basic methods for working with Maps: <literal>size()</literal>,
            <literal>isEmpty()</literal>, <literal>keySet()</literal>, <literal>values()</literal>,
          <literal>get(key)</literal>, <literal>put(key, value)</literal>, <literal>remove(key)</literal> and
            <literal>contains(key)</literal>. Each of these methods are equivalent to their Java counterpart. Where the
          method returns a collection, such as <literal>keySet()</literal> and <literal>values()</literal>, a Javascript
          Array object will be returned that contains the key or value objects (respectively). </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Debugging</title>

    <para> To aid in tracking down bugs, it is possible to enable a debug mode which will display the contents of all
      the packets send back and forth between the client and server in a popup window. To enable debug mode, either
      execute the <literal>setDebug()</literal> method in Javascript: </para>

    <programlisting role="XHTML">Seam.Remoting.setDebug(true);</programlisting>

    <para> Or configure it via components.xml: </para>

    <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<remoting:remoting debug="true"/>]]></programlisting>

    <para> To turn off debugging, call <literal>setDebug(false)</literal>. If you want to write your own messages to the
      debug log, call <literal>Seam.Remoting.log(message)</literal>. </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Handling Exceptions</title>
    
    <para>
      When invoking a remote component method, it is possible to specify an exception handler which will process
      the response in the event of an exception during component invocation.  To specify an exception handler function, 
      include a reference to it after the callback parameter in your JavaScript:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting><![CDATA[var callback = function(result) { alert(result); };
var exceptionHandler = function(ex) { alert("An exception occurred: " + ex.getMessage()); };
Seam.Component.getInstance("helloAction").sayHello(name, callback, exceptionHandler);]]></programlisting>
    
    <para>
      If you do not have a callback handler defined, you must specify <literal>null</literal> in its place:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting><![CDATA[var exceptionHandler = function(ex) { alert("An exception occurred: " + ex.getMessage()); };
Seam.Component.getInstance("helloAction").sayHello(name, null, exceptionHandler);]]></programlisting>    
    
    <para>
      The exception object that is passed to the exception handler exposes one method, <literal>getMessage()</literal>
      that returns the exception message which is produced by the exception thrown by the <literal>@WebRemote</literal>
      method.
    </para>
    
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Loading Message</title>

    <para> The default loading message that appears in the top right corner of the screen can be modified, its rendering
      customised or even turned off completely. </para>

    <section>
      <title>Changing the message</title>

      <para> To change the message from the default "Please Wait..." to something different, set the value of
          <literal>Seam.Remoting.loadingMessage</literal>: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML">Seam.Remoting.loadingMessage = "Loading..."; </programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Hiding the loading message</title>

      <para> To completely suppress the display of the loading message, override the implementation of
          <literal>displayLoadingMessage()</literal> and <literal>hideLoadingMessage()</literal> with functions that
        instead do nothing: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML">// don't display the loading indicator
Seam.Remoting.displayLoadingMessage = function() {};
Seam.Remoting.hideLoadingMessage = function() {};</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>A Custom Loading Indicator</title>

      <para> It is also possible to override the loading indicator to display an animated icon, or anything else that
        you want. To do this override the <literal>displayLoadingMessage()</literal> and
        <literal>hideLoadingMessage()</literal> messages with your own implementation: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML">  Seam.Remoting.displayLoadingMessage = function() {
    // Write code here to display the indicator
  };
  
  Seam.Remoting.hideLoadingMessage = function() {
    // Write code here to hide the indicator
  };</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Controlling what data is returned</title>

    <para> When a remote method is executed, the result is serialized into an XML response that is returned to the
      client. This response is then unmarshaled by the client into a Javascript object. For complex types (i.e.
      Javabeans) that include references to other objects, all of these referenced objects are also serialized as part
      of the response. These objects may reference other objects, which may reference other objects, and so forth. If
      left unchecked, this object "graph" could potentially be enormous, depending on what relationships exist between
      your objects. And as a side issue (besides the potential verbosity of the response), you might also wish to
      prevent sensitive information from being exposed to the client. </para>

    <para> Seam Remoting provides a simple means to "constrain" the object graph, by specifying the
      <literal>exclude</literal> field of the remote method's <literal>@WebRemote</literal> annotation. This field
      accepts a String array containing one or more paths specified using dot notation. When invoking a remote method,
      the objects in the result's object graph that match these paths are excluded from the serialized result packet. </para>

    <para> For all our examples, we'll use the following <literal>Widget</literal> class: </para>

    <programlisting role="JAVA">@Name("widget")
public class Widget
{
  private String value;
  private String secret;
  private Widget child;
  private Map&lt;String,Widget&gt; widgetMap;
  private List&lt;Widget&gt; widgetList;
  
  // getters and setters for all fields
}</programlisting>

    <section>
      <title>Constraining normal fields</title>

      <para> If your remote method returns an instance of <literal>Widget</literal>, but you don't want to expose the
          <literal>secret</literal> field because it contains sensitive information, you would constrain it like this: </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@WebRemote(exclude = {"secret"})
public Widget getWidget(); </programlisting>

      <para> The value "secret" refers to the <literal>secret</literal> field of the returned object. Now, suppose that
        we don't care about exposing this particular field to the client. Instead, notice that the
        <literal>Widget</literal> value that is returned has a field <literal>child</literal> that is also a
          <literal>Widget</literal>. What if we want to hide the <literal>child</literal>'s <literal>secret</literal>
        value instead? We can do this by using dot notation to specify this field's path within the result's object
        graph: </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@WebRemote(exclude = {"child.secret"})
public Widget getWidget();</programlisting>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Constraining Maps and Collections</title>

      <para> The other place that objects can exist within an object graph are within a <literal>Map</literal> or some
        kind of collection (<literal>List</literal>, <literal>Set</literal>, <literal>Array</literal>, etc). Collections
        are easy, and are treated like any other field. For example, if our <literal>Widget</literal> contained a list
        of other <literal>Widget</literal>s in its <literal>widgetList</literal> field, to constrain the
        <literal>secret</literal> field of the <literal>Widget</literal>s in this list the annotation would look like
        this: </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@WebRemote(exclude = {"widgetList.secret"})
public Widget getWidget();</programlisting>

      <para> To constrain a <literal>Map</literal>'s key or value, the notation is slightly different. Appending
          <literal>[key]</literal> after the <literal>Map</literal>'s field name will constrain the
        <literal>Map</literal>'s key object values, while <literal>[value]</literal> will constrain the value object
        values. The following example demonstrates how the values of the <literal>widgetMap</literal> field have their
          <literal>secret</literal> field constrained: </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@WebRemote(exclude = {"widgetMap[value].secret"})
public Widget getWidget(); </programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Constraining objects of a specific type</title>

      <para> There is one last notation that can be used to constrain the fields of a type of object no matter where in
        the result's object graph it appears. This notation uses either the name of the component (if the object is a
        Seam component) or the fully qualified class name (only if the object is not a Seam component) and is expressed
        using square brackets: </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@WebRemote(exclude = {"[widget].secret"})
public Widget getWidget(); </programlisting>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Combining Constraints</title>

      <para> Constraints can also be combined, to filter objects from multiple paths within the object graph: </para>

      <programlisting role="JAVA">@WebRemote(exclude = {"widgetList.secret", "widgetMap[value].secret"})
public Widget getWidget();</programlisting>
    </section>

  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Transactional Requests</title>
    
    <para>
      By default there is no active transaction during a remoting request, so if you wish to perform database updates 
      during a remoting request, you need to annotate the <literal>@WebRemote</literal> method with 
      <literal>@Transactional</literal>, like so:
    </para>
    
    <programlisting><![CDATA[  @WebRemote @Transactional(TransactionPropagationType.REQUIRED)
  public void updateOrder(Order order) {
    entityManager.merge(order);
  }]]></programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>JMS Messaging</title>

    <para> Seam Remoting provides experimental support for JMS Messaging. This section describes the JMS support that is
      currently implemented, but please note that this may change in the future. It is currently not recommended that
      this feature is used within a production environment. </para>

    <section>
      <title>Configuration</title>

      <para> Before you can subscribe to a JMS topic, you must first configure a list of the topics that can be
        subscribed to by Seam Remoting. List the topics under
          <literal>org.jboss.seam.remoting.messaging.subscriptionRegistry.allowedTopics</literal> in
          <literal>seam.properties</literal>, <literal>web.xml</literal> or <literal>components.xml</literal>. </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<remoting:remoting poll-timeout="5" poll-interval="1"/>]]></programlisting>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Subscribing to a JMS Topic</title>

      <para> The following example demonstrates how to subscribe to a JMS Topic: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML">function subscriptionCallback(message)
{
  if (message instanceof Seam.Remoting.TextMessage)
    alert("Received message: " + message.getText());
}           

Seam.Remoting.subscribe("topicName", subscriptionCallback);</programlisting>

      <para> The <literal>Seam.Remoting.subscribe()</literal> method accepts two parameters, the first being the name of
        the JMS Topic to subscribe to, the second being the callback function to invoke when a message is received. </para>

      <para> There are two types of messages supported, Text messages and Object messages. If you need to test for the
        type of message that is passed to your callback function you can use the <literal>instanceof</literal> operator
        to test whether the message is a <literal>Seam.Remoting.TextMessage</literal> or
          <literal>Seam.Remoting.ObjectMessage</literal>. A <literal>TextMessage</literal> contains the text value in
        its <literal>text</literal> field (or alternatively call <literal>getText()</literal> on it), while an
          <literal>ObjectMessage</literal> contains its object value in its <literal>value</literal> field (or call its
          <literal>getValue()</literal> method). </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Unsubscribing from a Topic</title>

      <para> To unsubscribe from a topic, call <literal>Seam.Remoting.unsubscribe()</literal> and pass in the topic
        name: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML">Seam.Remoting.unsubscribe("topicName");</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Tuning the Polling Process</title>

      <para> There are two parameters which you can modify to control how polling occurs. The first one is
          <literal>Seam.Remoting.pollInterval</literal>, which controls how long to wait between subsequent polls for
        new messages. This parameter is expressed in seconds, and its default setting is 10. </para>

      <para> The second parameter is <literal>Seam.Remoting.pollTimeout</literal>, and is also expressed as seconds. It
        controls how long a request to the server should wait for a new message before timing out and sending an empty
        response. Its default is 0 seconds, which means that when the server is polled, if there are no messages ready
        for delivery then an empty response will be immediately returned. </para>

      <para> Caution should be used when setting a high <literal>pollTimeout</literal> value; each request that has to
        wait for a message means that a server thread is tied up until a message is received, or until the request times
        out. If many such requests are being served simultaneously, it could mean a large number of threads become tied
        up because of this reason. </para>

      <para> It is recommended that you set these options via components.xml, however they can be overridden via
        Javascript if desired. The following example demonstrates how to configure the polling to occur much more
        aggressively. You should set these parameters to suitable values for your application: </para>

      <para> Via components.xml: </para>

      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<remoting:remoting poll-timeout="5" poll-interval="1"/>]]></programlisting>    

      <para> Via JavaScript: </para>

      <programlisting role="XHTML">// Only wait 1 second between receiving a poll response and sending the next poll request.
Seam.Remoting.pollInterval = 1;
  
// Wait up to 5 seconds on the server for new messages
Seam.Remoting.pollTimeout = 5;   </programlisting>

    </section>

  </section>

</chapter>
