<chapter id="tools">
  <title>Seam tools</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>jBPM designer and viewer</title>
  
     <para>
       The jBPM designer and viewer will let you design and view in a nice way your business processes and your pageflows.
       This convenient tool is part of JBoss Eclipse IDE and more details can be found in the jBPM's <ulink url="http://docs.jboss.com/jbpm/v3/gpd/">documentation</ulink>        
     </para> 
     
     <section>
       <title>Business process designer</title>
       
       <para>
         This tool lets you design your own business process in a graphical way.
       </para>
       
       <screenshot>
         <screeninfo>Business process designer</screeninfo>
         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject role="fo">
             <imagedata fileref="images/bpmd.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
           </imageobject>
           <imageobject role="html">
             <imagedata fileref="images/bpmd.png" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
       </screenshot>
       
     </section>
     
     <section>
       <title>Pageflow viewer</title>
       
       <para>
         This tool let you design to some extend your pageflows and let you build graphical views of them so you can
         easily share and compare ideas on how it should be designed.
       </para>
       
       <screenshot>
         <screeninfo>Business process designer</screeninfo>
         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject role="fo">
             <imagedata fileref="images/bpmpfv.png" align="center" scalefit="1"/>
           </imageobject>
           <imageobject role="html">
             <imagedata fileref="images/bpmpfv.png" align="center"/>
           </imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
       </screenshot>

      </section>

    </section>
    
    <!--
  <section>
    <title>CRUD-application generator</title>
    
    <para>
      This chapter, will give you a short overview of the support for Seam that is available in the Hibernate Tools.
      Hibernate Tools is a set of tools for working with Hibernate and related technologies, such as JBoss Seam and EJB3.
      The tools are available as a set of eclipse plugins and Ant tasks. You can download the Hibernate Tools from the JBoss Eclipse IDE or Hibernate Tools websites.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The specific support for Seam that is currently available is generation of a fully functional Seam based CRUD-application.
      The CRUD-application can be generated based on your existing Hibernate mapping files or EJB3 annotated POJO's or even fully
      reverse engineered from your existing database schema.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The following sections is focused on the features required to understand for usage with Seam. The content is derived from the the Hibernate Tools reference documentation. Thus if you
      need more detailed information please refer to the Hibernate Tools documentation.
    </para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Creating a Hibernate configuration file</title>

      <para>
        To be able to reverse engineer and generate code a hibernate.properties 
        or hibernate.cfg.xml file is needed. The Hibernate Tools provide a wizard for generating the
        hibernate.cfg.xml file if you do not already have such file.
      </para>

      <para>
        Start the wizard by clicking "New Wizard" (Ctrl+N), select the
        Hibernate/Hibernate Configuration file (cfg.xml) wizard and press "Next".
        After selecting the wanted location for the hibernate.cfg.xml file, you
        will see the following page:
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="/images/hibernatecfgwizard.gif" format="gif" contentwidth="5cm" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="/images/hibernatecfgwizard.gif"
                     format="gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>
        Tip: The contents in the combo boxes for the JDBC driver class and
        JDBC URL change automatically, depending on the Dialect and actual driver
        you have chosen.
      </para>

      <para>
        Enter your configuration information in this dialog. Details about
        the configuration options can be found in Hibernate reference
        documentation.
      </para>

      <para>
        Press "Finish" to create the configuration file, after optionally
        creating a Console onfiguration, the hibernate.cfg.xml will be
        automatically opened in an editor. The last option "Create Console
        Configuration" is enabled by default and when enabled i will automatically
        use the hibernate.cfg.xml for the basis of a "Console
        Configuration"
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating a Hibernate Console configuration</title>

      <para>
        A Console Configuration describes to the Hibernate plugin which configuration files
        should be used to configure hibernate, including which classpath is needed to load the POJO's,
        JDBC drivers etc. It is required to make usage of query prototyping, reverse engineering and
        code generation. You can have multiple named console configurations. Normally you would just
        need one per project, but more (or less) is definitly possible.
      </para>  

      <para>
        You create a console configuration by running the Console
        Configuration wizard, shown in the following screenshot. The same wizard
        will also be used if you are coming from the hibernate.cfg.xml wizard and
        had enabled "Create Console Configuration".
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
        <title>Creating a Hibernate Console configuration</title>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="/images/consolecfgwizard.gif" format="GIF" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="/images/consolecfgwizard.gif"
                     format="gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>
        The following table describes the relevant settings. The wizard can
        automatically detect default values for most of these if you started the
        Wizard with the relevant java project selected
      </para>

      <table>
        <title>Hibernate Console Configuration Parameters</title>
  
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />

          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3*" />

          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="1*" />

          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry align="center">
                <para>Parameter</para>
              </entry>

              <entry align="center">
                <para>Description</para>
              </entry>

              <entry align="center">
                <para>Auto detected value</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>

          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Name</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>The unique name of the configuration</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>Name of the selected project</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Property file</para>
              </entry>
  
              <entry>
                <para>Path to a hibernate.properties file</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>First hibernate.properties file found in the selected
                project</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Configuration file</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>Path to a hibernate.cfg.xml file</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>First hibernate.cfg.xml file found in the selected
                project</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Enable Hibernate ejb3/annotations</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>Selecting this option enables usage of annotated classes.
                hbm.xml files are of course still possible to use too. This
                feature requires running the Eclipse IDE with a JDK 5 runtime,
                otherwise you will get classloading and/or version
                errors.</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>Not enabled</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Mapping files</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>List of additional mapping files that should be loaded.
                Note: A hibernate.cfg.xml can also contain mappings. Thus if
                these a duplicated here, you will get "Duplicate mapping" errors
                when using the console configuration.</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>If no hibernate.cfg.xml file is found, all hbm.xml files
                found in the selected project</para>
              </entry>
            </row>

            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>Classpath</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>The classpath for loading POJO and JDBC drivers. Do not
                add Hibernate core libraries or dependencies, they are already
                included. If you get ClassNotFound errors then check this list
                for possible missing or redundant directories/jars.</para>
              </entry>

              <entry>
                <para>The default build output directory and any JARs with a
                class implementing java.sql.Driver in the selected
                project</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>Clicking "Finish" creates the configuration and shows it in the
      "Hibernate Configurations" view</para>

      <mediaobject>
        <title>Console overview</title>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" 
                     fileref="/images/consoleoutline-before-reveng.gif"
                     format="GIF" />
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="/images/consoleoutline-before-reveng.gif"
                     format="gif" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Reverse engineering and code generation</title>

      <para>
        A very simple "click-and-generate" reverse engineering and code
        generation facility is available. It is this facility that allows you to
        generate the skeleton for a full Seam CRUD application.
      </para>

      <para>
        To start working with this process, start the "Hibernate Code
        Generation" which is available in the toolbar via the Hibernate icon or
        via the "Run/Hibernate Code Generation" menu item.
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>Code Generation Launcher</title>

        <para>When you click on "Hibernate Code Generation" the standard Eclipse
        launcher dialog will appear. In this dialog you can create, edit and
        delete named Hibernate code generation "launchers".</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="/images/codegendropdown.gif" format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="/images/codegendropdown.gif"
                       format="gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>The dialog has the standard tabs "Refresh" and "Common" that can
        be used to configure which directories should be automatically refreshed
        and various general settings launchers, such as saving them in a project
        for sharing the launcher within a team.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="/images/codegenmaintab.gif" format="GIF" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="/images/codegenmaintab.gif"
                       format="gif" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>The first time you create a code generation launcher you should
        give it a meaningfull name, otherwise the default prefix
        "New_Generation" will be used.</para>

        <para>Note: The "At least one exporter option must be selected" is just
        a warning stating that for this launch to work you need to select an
        exporter on the Exporter tab. When an exporter has been selected the
        warning will disappear.</para>

        <para>On the "Main" tab you the following fields:</para>

        <table>
          <title>Code generation "Main" tab fields</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />

            <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3*" />

            <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="0.5*" />

            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center"><para>Field</para></entry>

                <entry align="center"><para>Description</para></entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry><para>Console Configuration</para></entry>

                <entry><para>The name of the console configuration which should
                be used when code generating.</para></entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry><para>Output directory</para></entry>

                <entry><para>Path to a directory into where all output will be
                written by default. Be aware that existing files will be
                overwritten, so be sure to specify the correct
                directory.</para></entry>
              </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Reverse engineer from JDBC
	              Connection</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>If enabled the tools will reverse engineer the
	              database available via the connection information in the
	              selected Hibernate Console Configuration and generate code based
	              on the database schema. If not enabled the code generation will
	              just be based on the mappings already specified in the Hibernate
	              Console configuration.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Package</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>The package name here is used as the default
	              package name for any entities found when reverse
	              engineering.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>reveng.xml</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>Path to a reveng.xml file. A reveng.xml file allows
	              you to control certain aspects of the reverse engineering. e.g.
	              how jdbc types are mapped to hibernate types and especially
	              important which tables are included/excluded from the process.
	              Clicking "setup" allows you to select an existing reveng.xml
	              file or create a new one..</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>reveng. strategy</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>If reveng.xml does not provide enough customization
	              you can provide your own implementation of an
	              ReverseEngineeringStrategy. The class need to be in the claspath
	              of the Console Configuration, otherwise you will get class not
	              found exceptions.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Generate basic typed composite ids</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>This field should always be enabled when generating the Seam CRUD application.
	              A table that has a multi-colum primary key a
	              &lt;composite-id&gt; mapping will always be created. If this
	              option is enabled and there are matching foreign-keys each key
	              column is still considered a 'basic' scalar (string, long, etc.)
	              instead of a reference to an entity. If you disable this option
	              a &lt;key-many-to-one&gt; instead. Note: a &lt;many-to-one&gt;
	              property is still created, but is simply marked as non-updatable
	              and non-insertable.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Use custom templates</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>If enabled, the Template directory will be searched
	              first when looking up the velocity templates, allowing you to
	              redefine how the individual templates process the hibernate
	              mapping model.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Template directory</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>A path to a directory with custom velocity
	              templates.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	          </tbody>
	        </tgroup>
	      </table>
	    </section>
	
	    <section>
	      <title>Exporters</title>
	
	      <para>The exporters tab is used to specify which type of code that
	      should be generated. Each selection represents an "Exporter" that are
	      responsible for generating the code, hence the name.</para>
	
	      <mediaobject>
	        <imageobject role="fo">
	          <imagedata fileref="/images/codegenselectseam.gif" format="GIF" />
	        </imageobject>
	
	        <imageobject role="html">
	          <imagedata align="center"
	                     fileref="/images/codegenselectseam.gif"
	                     format="gif" />
	        </imageobject>
	      </mediaobject>
	
	      <para>
	        The following table describes in short the various
	        exporters. The most relevant for Seam is of course the "JBoss Seam Skeleton app".
	      </para>
	
	      <table>
	        <title>Code generation "Exporter" tab fields</title>
	
	        <tgroup cols="2">
	          <colspec colnum="1" colwidth="1*" />
	
	          <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3*" />
	
	          <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="0.5*" />
	
	          <thead>
	            <row>
	              <entry align="center"><para>Field</para></entry>
	
	              <entry align="center"><para>Description</para></entry>
	            </row>
	          </thead>
	
	          <tbody>
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Generate domain code</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>Generates POJO's for all the persistent classes and
	              components found in the given Hibernate
	              configuration.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>JDK 1.5 constructs</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>When enabled the POJO's will use JDK 1.5
	              constructs.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>EJB3/JSR-220 annotations</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>When enabled the POJO's will be annotated according
	              to the EJB3/JSR-220 persistency specification.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Generate DAO code</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>Generates a set of DAO's for each entity
	              found.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Generate Mappings</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>Generate mapping (hbm.xml) files for each
	              entity</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Generate hibernate configuration
	              file</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>Generate a hibernate.cfg.xml file. Used to keep the
	              hibernate.cfg.xml uptodate with any new found mapping
	              files.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Generate schema html-documentation</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>Generates set of html pages that documents the
	              database schema and some of the mappings.</para></entry>
	            </row>
	
	            <row>
	              <entry><para>Generate JBoss Seam skeleton app
	              (beta)</para></entry>
	
	              <entry><para>Generates a complete JBoss Seam skeleton app. The
	              generation will include annotated POJO's, Seam controller beans
	              and a JSP for the presentation layer. See the generated
	              readme.txt for how to use it. </para><para>Note: this exporter
	              generates a full application, including a build.xml thus you
	              will get the best results if you use an output directory which
	              is the root of your project.</para></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      
      </section>
    
      <section>
        <title>Generating and using the code</title>
      
        <para>
          When you have finished filling out the settings, simply press "Run" to start the generation of code.
          This might take a little while if you are reverse engineering from a database.
        </para>
      
        <para>
	      When the generation have finished you should now have a complete skeleton Seam application in the output directory.
	      In the output directory there is a <literal>readme.txt</literal> file describing the steps needed to deploy and run the example.
        </para>
      
        <para>
          If you want to regenerate/update the skeleton code then simply run the code generation again by selecting the "Hibernate Code Generation" in the toolbar or "Run" menu. Enjoy.
        </para>
      </section>
    
    </section>
    
  </section>  
  -->
</chapter>
