<?xml version="1.0" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<chapter id="wicket">
   <title>Writing your presentation layer using Apache Wicket</title>

   <para>
      Seam supports Wicket as an alternative presentation layer to JSF. Take a 
      look at the <code>wicket</code> example in Seam which shows the Booking
      Example ported to Wicket.
   </para>

   <note>
      <para>
         Wicket support is new to Seam, so some features which are
         available in JSF are not yet available when you use Wicket
         (e.g. pageflow). You'll also notice that the documentation is
         very JSF-centric and needs reorganization to reflect the first
         class support for Wicket.
      </para>
   </note>
   
   <section>
      <title>Adding Seam to your wicket application</title>
      
      <para>
          The features added to your Wicket application can be split into two 
          categories: bijection and orchestration; these are discussed in detail
          below.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Extensive use of inner classes is common when building Wicket 
         applications, with the component tree being built in the constructor.
         Seam fully supports the use of annotation based control in inner 
         classes and constructors (unlike regular Seam components).
      </para>
      
      <para>
         Annotations are processed <emphasis>after</emphasis> any call to
         a superclass. This mean's that any injected attributes cannot be
         passed as an argument in a call to <code>this()</code> or 
         <code>super()</code>.
      </para>
      
      <note>
         <para>
            We are working to improve this.
         </para>
      </note>
      
      <para>
         When a method is called in an inner class, bijection occurs for any
         class which encloses it. This allows you to place your bijected
         variables in the outer class, and refer to them in any inner class.
      </para>
      
      <section>
         <title>Bijection</title>
         
         <para>
            A Seam enabled Wicket application has full access to the all the 
            standard Seam contexts (<code>EVENT</code>, <code>CONVERSATION</code>,
            <code>SESSION</code>, <code>APPLICATION</code> and
            <code>BUSINESS_PROCESS</code>).
         </para>
         
         <para>
            To access Seam component's from Wicket, you just need to inject it
            using <code>@In</code>:
         </para>
         
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@In(create=true)
private HotelBooking hotelBooking;]]></programlisting>

         <tip>
            <para>
               As your Wicket class isn't a full Seam component, there is no
               need to annotate it <code>@Name</code>.
            </para>
         </tip>
         
         <para>
            You can also outject an object into the Seam contexts from a Wicket
            component:
         </para>
         
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Out(scope=ScopeType.EVENT, required=false)
private String verify;]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            TODO Make this more use case driven
         </para>
      
      </section>
      
      <section>
         <title>Orchestration</title>
         
         <para>
            You can secure a Wicket component by using the 
            <code>@Restrict</code> annotation. This can be placed on the outer
            component or any inner components. If <code>@Restrict</code> is
            specified, the component will automatically be restricted to logged
            in users. You can optionally use an EL expression in the 
            <code>value</code> attribute to specify a restriction to be applied.
            For more refer to the <xref linkend="security"/>.
         </para>
         
         <para>
            For example:
         </para>
         
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[@Restrict
public class Main extends WebPage {

   ...]]></programlisting>
         
         <tip>
            <para>
               Seam will automatically apply the restriction to any nested
               classes.
            </para>
         </tip>
         
         <para>
            You can demarcate conversations from within a Wicket component
            through the use of <code>@Begin</code> and <code>@End</code>. The
            semantics for these annotations are the same as when used in a Seam
            component. You can place <code>@Begin</code> and <code>@End</code>
            on any method.
         </para>
         
         <note>
            <para>
               The deprecated <code>ifOutcome</code> attribute is not supported.
            </para>
         </note>
         
         <para>
            For example:
         </para>
         
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[item.add(new Link("viewHotel") {

   @Override
   @Begin
   public void onClick() {
      hotelBooking.selectHotel(hotel);
      setResponsePage(org.jboss.seam.example.wicket.Hotel.class);
   }
};]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            You may have pages in your application which can only be accessed 
            when the user has a long-running conversation active. To enforce 
            this you can use the <code>@NoConversationPage</code> annotation: 
         </para>
         
         <programlisting><![CDATA[@Restrict
@NoConversationPage(Main.class)
public class Hotel extends WebPage {]]></programlisting>

         <para>
            If you want to further decouple your application classes, you can 
            use Seam events. Of course, you can raise an event using
            <code>Events.instance().raiseEvent("foo")</code>. Alternatively, you
            can annotate a method <code>@RaiseEvent("foo")</code>; if the method
            returns a non-null outcome without exception, the event will be
            raised.
         </para>
         
         <para>
            You can also control tasks and processes in Wicket classes through
            the use of <code>@CreateProcess</code>, <code>@ResumeTask</code>,
            <code>@BeginTask</code>, <code>@EndTask</code>, 
            <code>@StartTask</code> and <code>@Transition</code>.
         </para>   
         
         <para>
            TODO - Implement BPM control - JBSEAM-3194
         </para>
      </section>
      
   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Setting up your project</title>
      
      <para>
         Seam needs to instrument the bytecode of your Wicket classes to be able
         to intercept the annotations you use. The first decision to make is: do
         you want your code instrumented at runtime as your app is running, or 
         at compile time?  The former requires no integration
         with your build environment, but has a performance penalty when loading each
         instrumented class for the first time.  The latter is faster, but requires 
         you to integrate this instrumentation into your build environment.
         </para>
      	 <section>
      	   <title>Runtime instrumentation</title>
      	   <para>
      	    There are two ways to achieve runtime instrumentation.  One relies on  
      	    placing wicket components to be instrumented in a special folder in your WAR
      	    deployment.  If this is not acceptable or possible, you can also use an
      	    instrumentation "agent," which you specify in the command line for launching
      	    your container.
      	    </para>
      	    <section>
      	    	<title>Location-specific instrumentation</title>
      	    	<para>
      	    	Any classes placed in the <literal>WEB-INF/wicket</literal> folder within your
      	    	WAR deployment will be automatically instrumented by the seam-wicket runtime.
      	    	You can arrange to place your wicket pages and components here by specifying
      	    	a separate output folder for those classes in your IDE, or through the use of 
      	    	ant scripts.
      	    	</para>
      	    </section>
      	    <section>
      	    <title>Runtime instrumentation agent</title>
  	    	<para>The jar file <literal>jboss-seam-wicket.jar</literal> can be used as an iinstrumentation 
  	    	agent through the Java Instrumentation api.  This is accomplished through the following
  	    	steps:</para>
  	    	<itemizedlist>
	  	    	<listitem>
		  	    	<para>Arrange for the <literal>jboss-seam-wicket.jar</literal> file to live in a 
		  	    	location for which you have an absolute path, as the Java Instrumentation API does 
		  	    	not allow relative paths when  specifying the location of an agent lib. </para>
	  	    	</listitem>
	  	    	<listitem>
		  	    	<para>Add <literal>javaagent:/path/to/jboss-seam-wicket.jar</literal> to the command line options 
		  	    	when launching your webapp container:</para>
	  	    	</listitem>
	  	    	<listitem>
		  	    	<para> In addition, you will need to add an environment variable that specifies 
		  	    	packages that the agent should instrument.  This is accomplished by a comma separated
		  	    	list of package names:</para>
		  	    	<programlisting>-Dorg.jboss.seam.wicket.instrumented-packages=my.package.one,my.other.package</programlisting>
		  	    	<para>Note that if a package A is specified, classes in subpackages of A are also examined.  The 
		  	    	classes chosen for instrumentation can be further limited by specifying:
		  	    	<programlisting>-Dorg.jboss.seam.wicket.scanAnnotations=true</programlisting>
		  	    	and then marking instrumentable classes with the <literal>@SeamWicketComponent</literal>
		  	    	annotation, see <xref linkend="SeamWicketComponent"/>.</para>
	  	    	</listitem>
  	    	</itemizedlist>
      	   </section>
      	 </section>
      	 <section>
      	   <title>Compile-time instrumentation</title>
      	   <para>
      	   Seam supports instrumentation at compile time through either Apache Ant or Apache Maven.</para>
      	   <section>
      	   <title> Instrumenting with ant</title>
      	   <para>
      	   Seam provides an ant task in the <literal>jboss-seam-wicket-ant.jar </literal>.  This is used
      	   in the following manner:
      <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<taskdef name="instrumentWicket" 
   classname="org.jboss.seam.wicket.ioc.WicketInstrumentationTask">
  <classpath>
    <pathelement location="lib/jboss-seam-wicket-ant.jar"/>
    <pathelement location="web/WEB-INF/lib/jboss-seam-wicket.jar"/>
    <pathelement location="lib/javassist.jar"/>
    <pathelement location="lib/jboss-seam.jar"/>
  </classpath>
</taskdef>

<instrumentWicket outputDirectory="${build.instrumented}" useAnnotations="true">
  <classpath refid="build.classpath"/>
  <fileset dir="${build.classes}" includes="**/*.class"/>
</instrumentWicket>]]></programlisting>
			</para>
      <para> 
		   This results in the instrumented classes being placed in the directory
		   specified by <literal>${build.instrumented}</literal>.  You will then
		   need to instruct ant to copy these classes into <literal>WEB-INF/classes</literal>. 
		   If you want to hot deploy the  Wicket components, you can copy the instrumented classes to 
         <literal>WEB-INF/dev</literal>; if you use hot deploy, make sure that
         your <literal>WicketApplication</literal> class is also hot-deployed.
         Upon a reload of hot-deployed classes, the entire WicketApplication 
         instance has to be  re-initialized, in order to pick up new references 
		   to the classes of mounted pages.
      </para>
      <para> The <literal>useAnnotations</literal> attribute is used to make the ant task only include
      classes that have been marked with the <literal>@SeamWicketComponent</literal> annotation, 
      see  <xref linkend="SeamWicketComponent"/>.
      </para>
     </section>
     <section>
     <title>Instrumenting with maven</title>
     <para>
     	The jboss maven repository <literal>repository.jboss.org</literal> provides a plugin named
     	<literal>seam-instrument-wicket</literal> with a <literal>process-classes</literal> mojo.  An
     	example configuration in your pom.xml might look like: 
     	<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<build>
		<plugins>
		 <plugin>
			<groupId>org.jboss.seam</groupId>
			<artifactId>seam-instrument-wicket</artifactId>
			<version>2.2.0</version>
			<configuration>
				<scanAnnotations>true</scanAnnotations>
				<includes>
					<include>your.package.name</include>
				</includes>
			</configuration>
			<executions>
				<execution>
					<id>instrument</id>
					<phase>process-classes</phase>
					<goals>
						<goal>instrument</goal>
					</goals>
				</execution>
			</executions>
		</plugin>
	</plugins>
</build>]]></programlisting>
		The above example illustrates that the instrumentation is limited to classes specified by
		the <literal>includes</literal> element.  In this example, the <literal>scanAnnotations</literal>
		is specified, see  <xref linkend="SeamWicketComponent"/>.
	</para>
	</section>
	</section>
	<section id="SeamWicketComponent">
	<title>The <literal>@SeamWicketComponent</literal> annotation</title>
	<para>
		Classes placed in WEB-INF/wicket will unconditionally be instrumented.  The other instrumentation 
		mechanisms all allow you to specify that instrumentation should only be applied to classes 
		annotated with the <literal>@SeamWicketComponent</literal> annotation.  This annotation is inherited,
		which means all subclasses of an annotated class will also be instrumented.  An example usage is:
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[import org.jboss.seam.wicket.ioc.SeamWicketComponent;
@SeamWicketComponent
public class MyPage extends WebPage{
 ...
}]]></programlisting>
	</para>
	</section>
     	
      
      <section>
         <title>Defining the Application</title>
      
         <para>
            A Wicket web application which uses Seam should use 
            <code>SeamWebApplication</code> as the base class; this creates hooks
            into the Wicket lifecycle allowing Seam to automagically propagate the
            conversation as needed. It also adds status messages to the page.
         </para>
         
         <para>
            For example:
         </para>
         
         <para>
            The <code>SeamAuthorizationStrategy</code> delegates authorization
            to Seam Security, allowing the use of <code>@Restrict</code> on Wicket
            components. <code>SeamWebApplication</code> installs the authorization
            strategy for you. You can specify the login page by implementing the
            <code>getLoginPage()</code> method. 
         </para>
         
         <para>
            You'll also need to set the home page of the application by 
            implementing the <code>getHomePage()</code> method.
         </para>
         
         <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[public class WicketBookingApplication extends SeamWebApplication {

   @Override
   public Class getHomePage() {
      return Home.class;
   }

   @Override
   protected Class getLoginPage() {
      return Home.class;
   }
   
}
]]></programlisting>
         
         <para>
            Seam automatically installs the Wicket filter for you (ensuring that
            it is inserted in the correct place for you). But you still need to 
            tell Wicket which <code>WebApplication</code> class to use. 
         </para>
         
         <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<components xmlns="http://jboss.com/products/seam/components"
 xmlns:wicket="http://jboss.com/products/seam/wicket"
 xsi:schemaLocation=
  "http://jboss.com/products/seam/wicket
   http://jboss.com/products/seam/wicket-2.2.xsd">
   
  <wicket:web-application 
    application-class="org.jboss.seam.example.wicket.WicketBookingApplication" />
</components]]></programlisting>
         
         <para>
          In addition, if you plan to use JSF-based pages in the same application as wicket pages, you'll 
          need to ensure that the jsf exception filter is only enabled for jsf urls:
         </para>
          
                   <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<components xmlns="http://jboss.com/products/seam/components"
 xmlns:web="http://jboss.com/products/seam/web"
 xmlns:wicket="http://jboss.com/products/seam/wicket"
 xsi:schemaLocation=
  "http://jboss.com/products/seam/web
   http://jboss.com/products/seam/web-2.2.xsd">
     
    <!-- Only map the seam jsf exception filter to jsf paths, which we identify with the *.seam path -->
	<web:exception-filter url-pattern="*.seam"/>
</components]]></programlisting>
          
          
         <tip>
            <para>
               Take a look at the Wicket documentation for more on authorization
               strategies and other methods you can override on the
               <code>Application</code> class.
            </para>
         </tip>
      </section>

   </section>

</chapter>
